<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true report of the late apprehension and imprisonnement of Iohn Nichols minister at Roan and his confession and ansvvers made in the time of his durance there. VVherevnto is added the satisfaction of certaine, that of feare or frailtie haue latly fallen in England.</title>
            <title>True report of the late apprehension and imprisonnement of John Nichols minister at Roan.</title>
            <author>Allen, William, 1532-1594.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08200</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105146</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840876</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840876</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5418</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08200)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5418)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 930:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true report of the late apprehension and imprisonnement of Iohn Nichols minister at Roan and his confession and ansvvers made in the time of his durance there. VVherevnto is added the satisfaction of certaine, that of feare or frailtie haue latly fallen in England.</title>
                  <title>True report of the late apprehension and imprisonnement of John Nichols minister at Roan.</title>
                  <author>Allen, William, 1532-1594.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34, [2] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Fogny,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Rhemes :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1583.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Allen by STC.</note>
                  <note>Appended: An admonition to the reader.</note>
                  <note>Allison &amp; Rogers.  Catholic Books, 12.</note>
                  <note>Several leaves stained and torn.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nichols, John.</term>
               <term>Prisoners' writings, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5418:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5418:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE REPORT OF THE LATE AP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PREHENSION AND IM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRISONNEMENT OF IOHN NICOLS Miniſter, at Roan, and his confeſſion and anſvvers made in the time of his durance there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVherevnto is added the ſatisfaction of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that of feare or frailtie haue latly fallen in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PRINTED AT RHEMES By Iohn Fogny. 1583.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:5418:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5418:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ood Chriſtian reader, the children, and ſpecially the Prieſts of Gods Church, haue ben manifoldly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailed by their aduerſaries in our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey theſe later yeres: firſt by the vvriting and preaching of the Sect-maiſters, vvhich made no great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion: Secondly by authoritie of the Ciuil Magiſtrate, vvhich vvas more forceible, but yet preuailed no further then to the loſſe of ſome rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens tranſitory goods, &amp; a fevv poore mens temporal liues, neither the one nor the other periſhed to the ovvners but both laid vp vvith Chriſt and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtovved vpon him to the hundreth fould aduantage in the next, and to
<pb facs="tcp:5418:3"/>the great encreaſe of the Catholike partie in this life.</p>
            <p>Laſtly by practiſe and pollicie of certain crafty co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celes men, by falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood &amp; forgerie, altering in the ſight of the ſimple the cauſes of their death &amp; puniſhment, &amp; making their liues &amp; actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s odious to the vvorld. Vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby they diſadua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taged in deede the Catholike part much more then by any plaine viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded iuſtice vvhatſoeuer. Beſides the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſions of Proteſtants but moſt falſe (though grounded vpon the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their ovvne diſloyaultie in the daies of Q. Mary) that al Catholikes be ennemies to the ſtate: vvas it not a great te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation to ſuch as knovv not the deepe ſubtiltie of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ſee that certain good fellovves vvere found to preach, print, &amp; aduouch to the faces of the poore deſolate perſons, yea and to ſvveare that they had purpoſed and
<pb facs="tcp:5418:3"/>practized the Queenes death? particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly recording the time, place, and circumſtances: and naming ſuch and ſuch of the Counſel, that vvere vvith all to be maſſacred, and al this, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo coulorably and confidently, or ſo plauſibly &amp; oportunely for the practize, that publike iuſtice paſſed vpon them as malefactors, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith many pretty pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phlets put forth and ſpred for the tempering of mens ſpeaches and conceits of ſuch ſtrange procedings. In this caſe truly a poore and vnaduiſed man might haue ben either for ſome time abuſed, or haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d good cauſe to ſay vvith the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete, <hi>Penè moti ſunt pedes mei:</hi> my feete vvere almoſt moued.</p>
            <p>But he that ſaid, nothing is hidd, vvhich ſhall not be reuealed, vvould not haue this error long to preuaile, but hath to his ovvne glory, the honor
<pb facs="tcp:5418:4"/>of his ſaincts and great aduantage of the Catholike cauſe in our countrey and the vvhol Church, many vvaies diſcouered that trechery: as ſhort gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies almoſt hath the ennimie of ſuch traffick, as Iudas had of the betraying and ſale of Chriſt, vvho diſcloſed his ovvne treaſon, yelded vp his money againe, and hanged him ſelf, before his Maiſter (vvhom he ſould) vvas executed. God giue the aduerſaries better grace and an other kind of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance then that proditor had: to ſaluation and not to perdition. But truely his name be therefore euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly glorified, our mercifull lord, hath merueilouſly reuealed to the ſhame of hereſie, theſe ſinful inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Churches ennemies.</p>
            <p>The conſcience and certen knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſo many good men, that knevv thoſe holy confeſſors inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,
<pb facs="tcp:5418:4"/>the vviſedom of others that ſavv the practiz, coulour, and collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the note of their anſvveres and full ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giuen at the barre, their vniforme and ſincere proteſtations of their innocencie at their death, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry qualities of ſuch perſons as vvere the firſt brochers and inſtruments of their accuſation and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, al theſe things and diuers trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes ſet forth of the matter, haue ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and made clere the caſe to the vvhol vvorld: vvhereby god of his old mercies hath turned all theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties and apparent diſtreſſes to the ſingular benefit of his truth.</p>
            <p>And lo here more, to ſee his ſvvet prouidence and diſpoſition of theſe things, <hi>Iohn Nichols</hi> him ſelf, the firſt author of the ſhamfull fiction, and that firſt ſet dovvne the particularities for vvhich the men of god vvere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb facs="tcp:5418:5"/>and executed, falling of late into the handes of the iuſtice at Roan, hath confeſſed al the colluſion and forgerie. Vvhich vvas thought meete to be publiſhed <hi>Verbatim,</hi> euen as him ſelf vvrote &amp; gaue forth to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and others: the Original partly remaining in the court roules, partly to be ſhevved of his ovvne hand vvriting.</p>
            <p>In ſetting it dovvne, no one title is altered, nor the very incongruities of his ſpeach amended. And though he vvas in priſon vvhen he did it, yet he did nothing of feare or compulſion, being aſſured that he could not for ſuch matters as he had committed in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, nor for religion, be any long time in durance in Fraunce: but al came of deepe remors of mind and conſcience for the death of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents, vvhich he knevv came by
<pb facs="tcp:5418:5"/>his falſe accuſation, vvherevvith he vvas invvardly ſo vexed in England, though he continued as he dooth yet in his peruerſe prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded religion, that he both confeſſed his foule dealing to one of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned perſons and to ſome in office and authoritie there: and alſo in fine left the Realme there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpecially, and partly, as he ſaith him ſelf, becauſe the Biſhops vvho vvere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded and had promiſed him euery one of them a yerely pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for recompence of that his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, vvould not keepe touch vvith him. but ſhaked him of vvith a <hi>Tu vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> like as the ievves did their copes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſudas. Vvhere vpon he obteined a peece of mony of an other, his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal patron, vvho thought it pitie or at leaſt no pollicie to caſt the poore miſer of, in that ſorte, and paſſed ouer into the lovve countrey vvithout ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:5418:6"/>his leaue, &amp; vvent forvvard into Germany, provvling as his manner hath long ben vvith Epiſtles for his liuing, and not finding co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentement ſo, he purpoſed into Turkey, and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thevvard he vvent on, till by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion one M. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Caddey ſometime ſtudent of the Engliſh College in <hi>Rome,</hi> he vvas turned back from that deſperat courſe into Fraunce: by vvhoſe godly endeuours for both their ſaluations, notice vvas giuen of the ſaid <hi>Nichols</hi> in <hi>Rhemes</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> and after vvas apprehended in <hi>Roan,</hi> vvhere he vvrote and ſpake the letters and other things follovving, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon vvas dimiſſed very ſhortly.</p>
            <p>And being aftervvard among ſome contreymen of his ovvne religion, to vvhom he reſorted for payment of his fees, he vvas demanded before
<pb facs="tcp:5418:6"/>them, by ſome that vvere Catholiks vvhether he vvould novv being at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, auouch all the things confeſſed in the time of his reſtraint: he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvered that all vvere moſt certaine, &amp; that he vvould ſtand to all that he had vttered. A proteſtant yet he vvould be ſtill, though in priſon he ſhovved him ſelf vvilling to conferre and to yeld to reaſon, and might at the ſame time haue eaſily ben inuited to <hi>Rhemes,</hi> if he had not falne into the Proteſtants hands, at his releaſing. At his firſt arriual in <hi>Roan,</hi> the vaine man told ſome of his companions that he had talked and diſputed vvith <hi>Doctor Allen,</hi> and that he profered him a hundred pound Engliſh a yere to be of his religion. The fellovves lif and fortune, though he be not old, hath ben exceding various, if all vvere recorded ſith he firſt vvas Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,
<pb facs="tcp:5418:7"/>vvhere his miſerie began: but nothing need to be ſpoken, of the cauſes of his firſt comming ouer ſea, of his follovving the Camp, of his vvandring in Flanders, Fraunce, and Italy, and ſuch like: onely I thought it neceſſarie for an introduction to the reſt, to ſet dovvne his formal Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration <hi>Verbatim,</hi> as it is recorded in the Court of Inquiſition at Rome: faithfully tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated into Engliſh. Into vvhich office of holy Iuſtice againſt Heretikes, he vvent to accuſe him ſelf of his ovvne accord, and in the end the matter paſſed as follovveth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="report">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5418:7"/>
            <head>A TRVE REPORT OF THE LATE APPREHENSION AND IMPRISONMENT OF IOHN NICOLS Miniſter, at Roan, and his confeſſion and anſwers made in the time of his dura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce there.</head>
            <head type="sub">Vvherevnto is added the ſatisfaction of certaine, that of feare or frailtie haue lately fallen in England.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The true copie of the Abiurations that Iohn Nicols (latly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſed from the Church by Apoſtaſie) made at Rome in the yere of our lord 1579. vvhich Abiurations, in his Engliſh reuolte latly publiſhed in print, are by him termed tvvo Sermons that he preached before the Popes holynes. faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſlated into Engliſh out of the auctentik Latine copie, nevvly ſent from Rome vvhere the Original is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of recorde.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OS Frater Thomas Zobbius ordinis praedicatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Sacrae Theologia Magiſter, &amp; Commiſſarius gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis, ſanctae &amp; vniuerſalis Inquiſitionis Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae. Cum tu Ioannes Nicolaus, filius alterius I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annis Nicolai de loco Vvalliae, Dioeceſis Landa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uienſis in Regno Angliae, aetatis tuae annorum viginti quatuor, velcirca, ſponte coram nobis comparueris in hoc ſancto Officio, atque confeſſus fueris, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vvee <hi>B. Thomas Zobbius</hi> of the order of the Preachers Doctor of diuinitie and Commiſſarie general of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly vniuerſal Inquiſition of Rome. For aſmuch as
<pb facs="tcp:5418:8"/>thou <hi>Iohn Nicols</hi> the ſonne of an other <hi>Iohn Nicols</hi> of the prouince of Vvales in the Dioceſſe of Landaff vvithin the Realme of England of the age of twenty and fower yeres or there abouts, haſt voluntarily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered before vs in this holy Office, and haſt confeſſed that after the Sacraments of Baptiſme &amp; Confirmation in thy childhod by thee rightly receiued after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the CATHOLIKE CHVRCH, thou haſt ben trained and brought vp in pernitious ſchiſme, and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry wicked hereſies vntill thou cameſt to the age of twenty and one yeres, and the ſame diddeſt beleeue, namely theſe, to vvite: Pilgrimages to holy places, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring of Candles and ſuch like, to be meere ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious. Beades not to be vſed. The Images of Saincts nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be had nor vvorſhiped. That Saincts ought not to be praied vnto: nor that they haue any care or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the neceſſities of mortall men, nor can pray for them. That praiers ought to be made in the vulgar tong which the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people vnderſtand. That lamps, aſhes, vvhich are put vpon the faithfull on Aſhwed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday, and al other ornaments and veſtements of the Church, and finally all ceremonies Eccleſiaſtical what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ought to be taken away. That it is lawfull for Prieſts to marry, and for all perſones to eate fleſh at all times. The Biſhop of Rome not to be head and cheef of the vniuerſall Church. That there is no Purgatorie after this life. That man hath not free will. That he is iuſtified by faith onely. The moſt bleſſed Sacrament of the body and blood of Chriſt, to be onely a ſigne of our lords paſſion, but not the body of our Sauiour IESVS CHRIST. That no Maſſe ought to be vſed in the Church, nor that the Apoſtles did celebrate any. That there are onely two Sacraments, that is to ſay: Baptiſme and the Lords ſupper.</p>
            <p>Finally that thou haſt preached vnto the people in many places the foreſaid hereſies, by the ſpace of one half yere, and that after the rites and manners of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes thou haſt taken the order of Deacon and Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
<pb facs="tcp:5418:8"/>and diddeſt obteine and get one benefice by Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, and an other by free gift, and the fruicts thereof diddeſt enioy by the ſpace of three yeres. And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as thou haſt ſaid, that thou art right ſory and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent for thoſe thy former errors, and that by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God thou art called to that faith vvhich our holy CATHOLIKE and APOSTOLICK mother the CHVRCH of ROME dooth beleeue and teach, and that thou mindeſt firmely to hold it, &amp; to ſtand therein to the death, and haſt humbly deſired that thou maiſt be admitted into the lappe of the holy Church, and to be abſolued from the cenſures Eccleſiaſticall which thou haſt incurred for thoſe cauſes, and to be diſpenſed with for ſuch irregularities as thou haſt thereby brought thy ſelf in danger of, and to haue remitted to thee ſuch fruicts as thou haſt taken of the ſaid benefices.</p>
            <p>The decree of the moſt honorable &amp; moſt Reuerend L. Cardinals Inquiſitors generall, in the publike aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the <hi>holy Inquiſition,</hi> by the counſel of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in diuinitie, and lavv, enacted the ſixth of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent moneth of May, being ſeene: whereby the diſpatche of this cauſe ſtanding in queſtion, betwene thee and the right worſhipfull and Reuerend Doctor <hi>Sig. Anſelme Canutus,</hi> Doctor of both lawes Canon and Ciuil, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curor fiſcal of this moſt holy Office, is committed to vs: we are come to pronounce this vndervvritten ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <p>The name of Chriſt and of that moſt glorious vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin his mother being firſt inuocated, we ſitting in the ſeate of the iudgement, and hauing onely God before our eyes, by this our definitiue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which we haue in this writing made, ſay, pronounce, iudge, decree, and declare thee, the foreſaid <hi>Iohn Nicols</hi> to haue ben a <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick</hi> and <hi>Heretick,</hi> and to haue incurred all the paines and puniſhments that are by the holy Cannons and Conſtitutions whatſoeuer general or ſpecial prouided and made againſt <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Hereticks.</hi> Yet for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as thou haſt voluntarily preſented thy ſelf before
<pb facs="tcp:5418:9"/>vs, proteſting that thou art ſory from thy hart, and haſt vvithall humilitie deſired to be admitted into the lappe of the holy ROMANE CHVRCH, vvhich is not vvont to be ſhut vp againſt ſuch as retorne therevnto: we doo benignely and mercifully receiue thee, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as thou requireſt, ſo that thou do deteſt, accurſe, and abiure from thy hart all ſchiſme and hereſies, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe aboue recited, and all errors that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and diſſonant to the ſaid holy CATHOLICK CHVRCH, in ſuch ſorte and manner as we commaund thee by this our definitiue ſentence, to accurſe, deteſt, &amp; ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re them.</p>
            <p>And yet to the intent, that <hi>Iuſtice</hi> be not vtterly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from <hi>Mercy,</hi> ſeing that the one is linked and knit vvith the other, and to the end the mercy of God by meane of Iuſtice may be more plentifull and large towards thee, we enioine thee for holſome penaunce, that thou do two ſeueral times viſite the ſeuen Churchs of this citie, and that all thy life time, thou ſay daily fiue times, <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and fiue times, the <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> and for the ſpace of fiue yeres, thou ſay once a vveeke, the <hi>Seuen penitentiall Pſalmes</hi> together vvith the <hi>Litanies</hi> and <hi>Praiers</hi> following: and once in the moneth, the office of the deade, called the <hi>Dirige.</hi> And that foure times in the yere of the ſaid fiue yeres, thou faſte, and euery moneth confeſſe thy ſinnes to a law full prieſt, ſuch as is allowed by his ordinarie, &amp; by his counſel and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent, to receiue the B. SACRAMENT of the altar once euery moneth, and in the feaſtes of the <hi>Natiuitie</hi> of our Lord, of <hi>Eaſter, Pentecost,</hi> and the <hi>Aſſumption</hi> of the gloriouſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual virgin <hi>Mary</hi> the mother of God.</p>
            <p>And ſo vvee do hereby Say, Iudge, Enioine, Decree, and Declare. Sending thee to the feete of our moſt holy Lord the POPES HOLINES for the forgiuenes of thy fructs taken, &amp; abſolution from the ſpot of <hi>Simony,</hi> and for the inhabling thee to holy orders, and other things vvhich are prohibited to <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> &amp; <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="report">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:5418:9"/>
            <head>THOMAS ZOBBIVS COMMISSARIE GENERAL.</head>
            <p>The aboue vvritten ſentence, vvas giuen, avvarded, and iudicially pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by this vvriting, by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named our reuerend father <hi>Thomas de Zobbiis</hi> of the order of the preachers, Doctor of diuinitie, Commiſſioner general of the Office of the holy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and vniuerſal <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> ſitting in the Iudgement ſeat at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of the ſaid holy office in the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tican</hi> of <hi>S. Peter:</hi> &amp; vvas read &amp; publiſhed by me the Notarie, at the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſaid reuerend father the Commiſſarie, in the yere of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of our Sauiour 1579. in the ſeuenth indiction, the viij. day of the moneth of May, in the time of the Biſhoprick &amp; See of our ſoueraigne and moſt holy Father in Chriſt <hi>Gregorie</hi> by Gods prouidence the <hi>thirteenth</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:5418:10"/>that name, the ſaid <hi>Iohn Nichols</hi> being preſent, and vvith thanks giuing, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the foreſaid ſentence: vvho vvilling to obey the ſame, and all the contentes thereof, kneeling vpon his knees before the ſaid reuerend Father Commiſſarie general of the holy of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, corporally touching vvith his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds the holy ſcriptures, did <hi>Abiure, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Deteſt,</hi> al thoſe errors &amp; ſchiſme, and the hereſies vvhich he helde and beleeued in manner and forme as in the <hi>Abiuration</hi> hereafter follovving, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed vvith his ovvne hand may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peere: made at <hi>Rome</hi> in the pallace of the ſaid holy office, then and there being preſent as vvitneſſes, <hi>Benedictus de Solanis, Peruzin,</hi> and <hi>Petrus Bilaqua</hi> of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Firmiano.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>Iohn Nichols,</hi> the ſonne of an other <hi>Iohn Nichols,</hi> of the prouince of <hi>Vvales,</hi> of the Dioces of <hi>Landaf,</hi> in the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> of the age of tvventy and fower yeres, or there about, kneeling on my knees before the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erend Father <hi>Thomas Zobbius</hi> of the order of the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5418:10"/>Doctor of Diuinitie, and Commiſſioner general of the office of the holy and vniuerſal <hi>Inquiſition</hi> of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me:</hi> touching perſonally the holy Goſpels, do ſweare, that I beleeue and vvil to my death beleeue, that faith vvhich the holy CATHOLICK and APOSTOLICK ROMAN CHVRCH doth beleeue and teach.</p>
            <p>But for ſo much as after the Sacraments of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and <hi>Confirmation</hi> rightly and Catholikely by me receiued and taken in my childhood, I vvas brought vp and trained in pernitious ſchiſme, and ſundry moſt impious hereſies, till I came to the age of twenty and one yeres, and them did beleeue, namely and ſpecially: That Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages to holy places, Offring vp of candles, &amp; ſuch like, were meere ſuperſtitious. That praying vpon beads ought not to be vſed: That the images of Saincts ought neither to be vvorſhipped nor had: That the Saincts in heauen ought not to be praied vnto, nor that they haue any regard, care, or knowledge of the neceſſities of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal men, nor can pray for them. That praiers ought to be made in the vulgar tong, which the common people doo vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. That Candles, Aſhes, which are vſed to be put on the faithful vpon Aſhweneſday, all orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and ſtuf of the Church, and finally, all Ceremonies ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical whatſoeuer ought quite to be taken avvay. That it is lawful for Prieſts to marry, and for all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones daily to eate fleſh. That the Biſhop of Rome is not the head of the vniuerſall Church of Chriſt. That there is no Purgatorie, after this life. That man hath no free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvil, &amp; is iuſtified by onely faith. That the moſt bleſſed Sacrament of the body and blood of Chriſt, is onely a ſigne of the death &amp; paſſion of our Lord, but not his very body. That no Maſſe ought to be vſed in the Church or was celebrated by the Apoſtles. That there are onely tvvo Sacramentes, to wite: Baptiſme, and the Lords ſupper. And theſe hereſies haue I preached by the ſpace of half a yere, and after the rite and manner of hereticks, haue receiued the order of Deaconſhip and Prieſthood, and obteined one Eccleſiaſticall benefice by
<pb facs="tcp:5418:11"/>
               <hi>Simonie,</hi> and an other of gift, and receiued the fruicts thereof. And for theſe cauſes was adiuged by this holy office a Schiſmatick and Heretick.</p>
            <p>I therfore do from my hart, Abhorre, Deteſt, and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure, all ſchiſme and hereſies, namely thoſe aboue ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. And ſweare that neuer hereafter will I beleeue he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies or keepe company with hereticks, or read their books. And do further ſwere that I wil denounce and declare vnto this holy court, and to the inquiſitors and ordinaries, of the places in the vvhich I ſhal become, al and ſingular perſones whom I ſhal know either to be profeſſed hereticks, or ſuſpected of hereſie. And ſwere alſo, that I wil obſerue and performe al the points of the penance enioyned me: and in caſe I do not. I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect my ſelf to al the paines and puniſhements due by the law, to ſuch offendors, ſo help me God, and theſe moſt holy Goſpels.</p>
            <p>I the foreſaid <hi>Iohn Nicols</hi> haue <hi>Svvorne, Abiured,</hi> and <hi>Promiſed</hi> as before: and in faith thereof this ſchedull written vvith an other hand, I haue ſubſcribed vvith mine owne: At <hi>Rome</hi> in the Palace of the ſaid holy office, the viij. day of the moneth of <hi>May, Anno</hi> 1579.</p>
            <p>VVhich Abiuration being made, the foreſaid Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father Commiſſarie general, did abſolue the ſaid <hi>Iohn Nicols</hi> there preſent and moſt humbly vpon his knees erauing the ſame, and him diſcharged from the Excommunications, Cenſures, and Penalties by him incurred by reaſon and cauſe of the premiſes, and him reſtored to the communion of the faithful, to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of the Sacraments, and to the vnitie and lap of our ſaid holy mother the CATHOLICK CHVRCH. And hath enioyned him for healthful penance as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the aboue written ſentence, recorded and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentiked as is before ſaid, in the preſence of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named witneſſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <p>This copie vvas taken out of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5418:11"/>firſt &amp; proper Original, vvith vvhich (vponco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce made) it agreeth &amp;c. In faith and vvitnes vvhereof I haue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and ſealed it vvith the ſeale of the ſaid holy Office in ſuch caſes vſed. At Rome in the Palace of the ſaid holy Office the thirteenth of the ſaid moneth of Maij 1579. So it is, Signed by me <hi>Flaminius Adrianus</hi> Notary of the holy Romane &amp; general Inquiſition in faith and teſtimonie of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p>LAVRENCE CADDEY of whom we made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before, lately paſſing the ſeas vvith <hi>Iohn Nicols,</hi> and his fellow in iourney into <hi>Germany,</hi> daily concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more and more ſorrow of the miſery he was falne into by his frailtie and coacted forſaking of the vnitie of the CATHOLICK CHVRCH, retired into <hi>France</hi> in Ianuary laſt <hi>An.</hi> 1583. and his ſaid Companion with him: and approching neere <hi>Rhemes,</hi> whither he came for his comfort of conſcience, being in a village neere the ſuburbs of the Citie, he made his vvay by this letter written to the Preſident of the College, as followeth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I might comme to the Citie of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> becauſe I neuer offended the ſame, or any inhabitant thereof: yet in reſpect of you my deere country men. I neither will come thither or vnto you, although as I ſhall be ſaued at the daie of iudgement, I loue you, and
<pb facs="tcp:5418:12"/>haue loued you as the apple of mine eye. And although the deſire I haue to ſpeake with you be vnſpeakeable, the matter for the which I would ſpeake with you is the greateſt that euer I had with any ſince I was borne, or can haue whiles I liue in this miſerable vvorld, and as I hope more profitable both for ſoule and bodie then any thing whatſoeuer in this world Beſides it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth to both the Seminaries, that of <hi>Rome,</hi> and this of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> concerning vvaightie matters in reſpect of them both. Moreouer it concerneth the abhominable lyes of <hi>Iohn Nicols,</hi> which hereby may be redreſſed. To conclude, if your Seminaries haue ben iniured by the ſclaunders of any, hereby they may be I truſt cleared againe: and I truſt that in reſpect of ſome, it may be ſaid that the ſame Scorpion that ſtinged being cruſhed on the ſame, wil ſoneſt heale the wound ſhe made.</p>
                  <p>Therfore M. Doctor <hi>Allen,</hi> I requeſt you for the loue you beare to Chriſt crucified, his bleſſed mother, and all the Saincts of heauen, &amp; as you te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the life of a ſoule almoſt deade in ſinne deſiring by your meanes to be quickened, and as you couit to heale the ſores vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, your Seminaries haue ben wounded, ſend in all haſt without any delay a Prieſt wel learned, vertuous, and mortified, and of a good nature, and to him largely the cauſe of my arriual here, I wil lay open, ſo that by him you may be fully certified thereof. the which I would haue to be either M. <hi>Gregorie Marten,</hi> or Doctor <hi>Barnard</hi> the neede of body bringeth me not hither, but of Soule, and cauſes alleged. I am at <hi>Teſsi</hi> half a league from you in a tauerne: hither therfore ſend as I requeſt with this meſſenger in all haſt that can be, and if the ſaid Prieſt lodged here al night it were beſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your humble Orator. laden vvith ſinne, vviſhing and comming hither to be healed, whoſe name you ſhall knovv.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Poſt ſcriptum.</hi> I haue a letter from the ſaid <hi>Nicols</hi> to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5418:12"/>your worſhip, who is on this ſide the ſea which I wil deliuer to the Prieſt ſent.</p>
                     <p>It vvas endorced thus.</p>
                     <p>Venerabili viro D. Doctori Alano Anglorum Seminarij Rhemenſis digniſsimo pręſidi, hae ſtatim tradantur litera.</p>
                     <p>A Monſieur le Docteur Allen Anglois. Ieſus Maria. Si non ſit in Ciuitate D. Alanus, tradantur Doctori Bernardo, aut D. Gregorio Martino.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THe Preſident being not then at home, but nevvly gone to <hi>Paris,</hi> this letter was receiued and reade by the other to vvhom in his abſence it vvas directed, and by whom his godly deſire was alſo in part accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: but for more ful ſatisfaction of his conſcience, he was aduiſed to go forvvard to <hi>Paris,</hi> vvhere he might deale vvith D. <hi>Allen</hi> him ſelf: and ſo he reſolued to doo, hauing appointed alſo before to meete <hi>Iohn Nicols</hi> againe there, vvho departed from him (as he ſaid) at <hi>Challon,</hi> ten leagues from <hi>Rhemes,</hi> where <hi>Nicols</hi> (for a <hi>Brauado</hi>) wrot this letter follovving to the ſaid Doctor: vvhich letter, at once vvith <hi>Laurence Caddeyes,</hi> he receiued by a ſpecial and ſpeedy meſſager, before <hi>Laurence</hi> him ſelf arriued</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Octor</hi> Alane, <hi>multi te ferunt librum quendam edidiſſe ſub nomine</hi> Apologiae <hi>diuulgatum vtriúſque Seminarij</hi> Romae Rhemiſque <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani Pontificis impenſis extructi. In eo libro tuo nimis in me ferociter irruiſti &amp; maledictis la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsiuiſti, ſi tu aliqua ſalutis meae cupiditate flagraſſes illa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitia atque maledicta quibus abundaſti ſilentio pretermiſiſſes. Satis in meum vituperium dixiſſe arbitratus es, cum dixeras me
<pb facs="tcp:5418:13"/>his deciuiſſe à religione veſtra, quid hoc ad propoſitum, nunquid Apoſtoli (qui omnibus virtutis ornamentis exculti fuerant) ſemper Chriſtum agnouerunt? minime gentium ſed Chriſtum aliquando negauerunt vt ſacra ſcripturarum loca teſtantur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quid ſi ego veſtram religionem (ſi vera eſſet religio) decies abnegaſſem, &amp; poſtea eam amplexus fuiſſem quandiu vixiſſem, nunquid poſt miſeram hanc vitam me reprobum ſentiretis? pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectò haud ſic, ſi veri Chriſtianieſſetis. veſtram religionem mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis erroribus implicatam denegaſſe laetor, maximè ſi fides veſtra Romana ab Apoſtolorum ſententia mintmè diſſentiret, ab illa nullis terrortbus atque ſuppliciis adduci vllo modo potuiſſem: ſed quia traditionibus humanis innititur, illam non probo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alane <hi>mi, Conſule tibi dum tempus eſt, Reſipiſce, Renuncia erroribus quibus irretiris, Reuertere in patriam, Proſternas te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum ad pedes pientiſsimae Reginae noſtrae, explices perfidiam tuam, deplora te talem fuiſſe qualem terra vt ferret indignus fuiſti. Romae quid didici? hypocriſim, mendacium, arrogatiam, breuiter, omnia mala. in Seminario regnat libido, ſuperbia, inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, ira, maledicentia, vt breui comprehendam, illud collegium eſt ſentina omnium malorum. Perhorreſco literis mandare quae oculis meis vidi, non crederes, quia nimis faues illis. Raptim ſcripſi. Reſcribe ſi vis, aut ſi elatus animus patietur. ſcriptum Nancy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed> Per me Ioannem Nicolaum Anglum. </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Octor Allen, manie reporte that you haue publiſhed a booke vnder the title of an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of both the Seminaries of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Rhemes,</hi> erected at the <hi>Popes</hi> charges. In that booke you haue puſhed at me very furiouſly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked me vvith many reproches. If you had had any care of my ſoules health, you vvould haue paſſed ouer thoſe reproches and detractions vvith ſilence: but you thought to diſgrace me excedingly in reporting that I had tvviſe forſaken your religion. what is that to the purpoſe? vvhy? did the Apoſtles (vvhich were adorned vvith all ornaments of vertue) alvvaies confeſſe Chriſi?
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5418:13"/>nothing leſſe. For ſometimes they did denie him as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vvrit teſtifieth.</p>
                  <p>Vvhat if I had denied your Religion ten times (if it vvere a true religion) and aftervvard had embraced it againe as long as I liued, would you notvvithſtanding haue taken me for a reprobate after my death? if you vvere true Chriſtians, I thinke you vvould not. I am ful glad that I haue denied your Religion, vvhich is mixed vvith manie errors. If your Romane faith diſſented not from the doctrine of the Apoſtles, I ſhould neuer haue ben dravven from it, vvith terrors or torments what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer: but becauſe it is vnderpropped vvith mens tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, I cannot like or allovv of it.</p>
                  <p>O <hi>M. Allen,</hi> prouide for your ſelf vvhile you haue time. Amende, and for ſake your errors vvherewith you are entangled. Retourne home to your country. Caſt your ſelf downe at the feete of our merciful Queene. Confeſſe your diſloyaultie, and lament that you haue ben ſuch a one, as the earth is vnworthie to beare. what learned I at <hi>Rome?</hi> hypocriſie, lying, pride, and to be ſhort al that euel is. In that Seminarie there, raigneth luſt, pride, enuie vvrathe, detraction, and to ſay al at a worde, that College is the ſinke of ſinne. I do tremble to vvrite the things, that I haue ſeene vvith mine eyes: neither vvould you beleeue them, becauſe you fauor them to much. I haue vvritten in haſt, vvrite againe if you vvil, or if your prowde ſtomack will ſuffer you. Vvritten at <hi>Nancy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>By me Iohn Nicols Engliſhman.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>ABout three daies after the receipt of the aboue written letters, came <hi>Laurence Caddey</hi> and found <hi>D. Allen</hi> and all other Catholicks very redy, as duty requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to giue him the comfort and ſuccour they could to his great contentement: as alſo vpon intelligence that <hi>Iohn Nichols</hi> vvas in the tovvne, many meanes vvere
<pb facs="tcp:5418:14"/>ſought to bring him to conference and ſpeach of the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arned for his recouery: but miſſing of that, there vvas thought no other remedy to ſaue his ſoule, &amp; to reclame him from the damnable ſtate that he liued and vvas like to dy in: but by his apprehenſion and impriſonning, vvhich, by reaſon of his ſpeedy departure from <hi>Paris,</hi> could not be donne there: but it vvas atchiued at <hi>Roan,</hi> vvhere vpon his reſtraint, he vvrot vvith his ovvne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at ſeuerall times the letters and others things in Latine, to <hi>D. Allen.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Octor Alane, tua meam petulantiam vicit charitas, ad te (temeritate ductus magis quam prudentia fretus) acriter ſcripſi, tu ira non commotus omnia bona mihi optaſti, pollicitus es cum fueram tibi inimicus ea quae non ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raueram à te concedi, tua elementia me ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauit ſupra modu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Pariſiis Rhemos veniſſem ſi mea culpata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta non fuiſſet quantum explicare verbis nequeo. Pudore impeditus, Rhemos petere nolim. Tua patientia mea maior fuit malitia, tua verba ex charitate fraterna producta oſtenderunt quo ſpiritu ſuffultus eras. Laurentius Caddeus, qui meas tibi dedit lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, iuramento facto predicta confirmauit, qua charitate audita in quae prorupi verba teſtetur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Si illam Domine D. Alane animae meae curam te habere ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſit, vt tuam reuerentiam non pigeret peregrinationis multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum locorum modo ſaluares eam, des tunc operam vt ſaluetur. &amp; mea anima ſalua tua opera, ſaluabitur anima tua iuxta ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum diuinum. Si anima &amp; corpore peribo tua incuria atque ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligentia, redditurus es rationem huiuſmodi mortis meae in die iudicij. Sum detentus in carceribus, &amp; non indignè. Suſtentor lautius hucuſque quam deberem, appello ad tuam reuerentiam, &amp; non ad Papae Nuntium. Si promittes tuis literis, quod mea culpa quoquo modo commiſſa contra quoſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que ignoſcetur mihi, &amp; quod nemo ob mea delicta perpetrata, me è medio tollere cona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur, Rhemos veniam, &amp; ponam vitam meam in manibus tuis: ſi hoc mihi negabis, ſanguis meus à te requiretur, &amp; eris cauſa perditionis animae meae. Non curo propter vitam corporis mei.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5418:14"/>ſingulis diebus contentus ſum mori, ſi ſemel animam meam &amp; virtute &amp; religione verbo diuino innixam, ſuffultam ſentirem, oh nemo mortalium me laetior eſſet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dicunt multi me nullam religionem habere, &amp; verè dicunt ſecundum opera mea, flagitiis enim multis coopertus ſum. hoc ego dico et in ſuggeſtu ſepe dixi. Quodcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que ſcriptum eſt in vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatque nouo teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to firmiter credo ſi me ad ignem, autad pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulum lictores iam traherent, aliud non crederem, inſtar vmbrae eſt vita mea, à carcere Rothomagenſi clamo ad te vir magne, &amp; vir plene charitatis vt mihi ſuccurras dum hac vitae vſura fruor. Si conquaereris de ſcriptis meis, quod falſum eſt retractabo, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam indicabo cur ſic ſcripſeram, totam mentem meam iuxta veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis limites ſatis abundè explicabo. D. Alane, etſi grauiter of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenderam, tamen curam tibi committo animae meae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Neſcio quid de me conſultum eſt, ſi Papa &amp; Cardinales, &amp; omnes alij qui autoritate praecedunt alios, conſultius aeſtimant eſſe vt vindictam ſumant iniuriae illatam illis immeritò, fiat vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas Domini, ſciunt vbi me inueniant: exequantur quod in mentem venit, ſed aliter de illorum charitate ſpero. In his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtiis quibus conſtitutus ſum D Alane, praeſto mihi ſis, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio &amp; labore &amp; aliis omnibus charitatis operibus: &amp; accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labis tibi magnum theſaurum in caelis, &amp; me tibi in aeuum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non ſum obſtinatus, cupio ſaluus eſſe, ſaluum me reddat Deus anima à corpore diſſoluta. Scripſi. bene vale, oraque pro me peccatore maximo. Dum viuo, ſpero Redde bonum D Alane pro malo, &amp; eris diſcipulus Chriſti: ſic fecit Chriſtus, ſic docuit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Per me Ioannem Nicolaum Anglum, tui amantiſſimum.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>POſt ſcriptum. <hi>Spiritus pugnat contra carnem, caro contra ſpiritum ad tempus ſpiritus diluuio peccatorum ſubmerſus carni ſuccubuit, ſed ſpero quod ſpiritus emergetur, &amp; carnis vires mulalidabit Deus ſit mihi propitius. Capituitas eſt medium per quod viam ad coelum inueniam D. Alane, partim quia Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum agnoſcis, &amp; partim quia conterraneus meus es, conſule mihi dum tempus eſt. Lego veſtros libros, non taedet me legere, aliquam
<pb facs="tcp:5418:15"/>mihi legendo conſolationem comparaui. Legam, &amp; ſermonem ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere cum Catholicis Romanis inficias non ibo. Scripſi, &amp; expecto reſponſionem voluntatis tuae propenſae, vt ſpero in meam ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi> 18. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1583.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Per me peccatorem grauiſſimum, Ioannem Nicolaum indignum hac vita quam dego.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Octor Allen,</hi> Your charitie hath ouercome my impudencie. I wrote vnto you very ſharpely, being led thereto rather through raſhenes, then guided by wiſdome. you for your owne part being nothing atal moued therevvith to anger, vviſhed al good vnto me promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to me your enmmie ſuch benefits as I could not haue looked for at your hands. your clemencie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath vvonderfully vanquiſhed me. I would haue come from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Rhemes,</hi> if my offence had not ben ſo haynous, as cannot be by wordes expreſſed. The cauſe why I came not to <hi>Rhemes,</hi> was, becauſe I was aſhamed of my ſelf. Your Pacience is greater then my mallice. Your wordes proceeding from brotherly charitie, do declare with what ſpirit you are endewed. <hi>Laurence Caddey</hi> vvho deliuered my former letter vnto you, hath affirmed the fore ſaid things to be true and that with an other he alſo can witnes into what ſpeaches I burſt forth vvhen I vnderſtood this your charitie.</p>
                  <p>If it be true <hi>(M.D. Allen)</hi> that you haue ſo great care of my ſoule, that your Reuerence vvould not ſticke to trauaile to what place ſoeuer, to ſaue it: do you your endeuour then to ſaue it. For if my ſoule be ſaued by your meanes, you ſhall ſaue your owne ſoule alſo, as holy writ ſaith: but if I doo periſh bodie and ſoule by your careleſſnes and negligence you are to render ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt thereof at the daie of Iudgement. I am empri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, and that worthely: and am fedd hitherto more delicatly then I haue deſerued. I do appeale to your
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5418:15"/>worſhip and not to the Popes <hi>Nunce.</hi> And if you will promis me by your letters that the faults vvhich I haue by any meanes whatſoeuer committed againſt any man, ſhalbe forgiuen me, and that no man ſhal purſue me to death for the crimes that I haue committed, I will come to <hi>Rhemes,</hi> &amp; yeld my ſelf into your hands: if you deny me this, my bloud ſhalbe required at your hands, and you ſhalbe the cauſe of the loſſe of my ſoule. I eſteeme not this tranſitorie life, I am content to dye, and that euery daie. Oh if I felt once my ſoule to be endewed with vertue &amp; religion ſtaied vpon Gods holie word, no man vvould be more glad then I ſhould be.</p>
                  <p>Many report that I haue no religion in me, and they ſaie truely in reſpect of my vvorks, for I am ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with many abhominable vices. I ſay thus much &amp; haue often ſaid it out of the pulpit. That I doo firmely beleeue whatſoeuer is vvritten in the old and new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. If the Sergants were drawing me to the fire or gallowes, I would not beleeue any other thing. My life is like a ſhadowe, I crie to you (worſhipfull Sir and full of charitie) out of the priſon of <hi>Roan,</hi> to aſſiſt me whiles yet I liue. If you complaine of my books, I will retract that which is falſe, I will ſhewe the cauſe vvhy I wrot ſo. I vvill open my mind aboundantly ſo far as the limites of truth will permit. <hi>M.D. Allen</hi> albeit I haue greuouſly offended, that notwithſtanding I commit the care of my ſoule vnto you.</p>
                  <p>I know not vvhat the <hi>Pope, Cardinals,</hi> and others in authoritie ar determined to do with me: if they thinke it beſt to take vengeance on me for the iniuries vvhich I haue vniuſtly donne vnto them, the lords will be donne: they know where to finde me, let them put their deſignes in execution hardly: but for all that I hope better of their charitie. Being brought into theſe diſtreſſes, I beſeech you <hi>D. Allen</hi> to aſſiſt me with coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and al other works of charitie, and you ſhal thereby heape to your ſelf a treaſure in heauen, and ſhall binde me to be yours foreuer. I am not obſtinate. God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I
<pb facs="tcp:5418:16"/>may be ſauued after this life. I haue written. Fare you well, and pray for me a greuous ſinner: for as long as I liue, I will hope. <hi>M.D. Allen,</hi> render good for euil, and by ſo doing you ſhalbe Chriſte his diſciple. For ſo Chriſt did, ſo he taught,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>By me, Iohn Nichols Engliſman, your louer.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>POſt ſcriptum.</hi> The ſpirit doth fight againſt the fleſh, and the fleſh againſt the ſpirit: and for a time the ſpirit being ouer whelmed with the flood of ſinnes, doth yeeld vnto the fleſh, but I hope that the ſpirit will get the victorie, and weaken the force of the fleſh. God be merciful vnto me. Impriſonment is a meanes by which I may finde the way to heauen. <hi>M. D. Allen</hi> helpe me vvith your aduice whiles time is: partely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are a Chriſtian man: partly alſo, becauſe you are my country man. I reade your bookes and am not weary of reading, I haue gained great comfort &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation by reading them. I will reade ſtill and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe no conference with any <hi>Roman Catholik.</hi> I haue written, and novv expecte your fauorable anſwere, as I hope, to my ſaluation. 18. Feb. 1583.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>By me moſt greuous ſinner, Iohn Nicols, vnvvorthy to liue.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Octor Alane, contra Papam, Cardinales &amp; Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos quaecunque ſcripſi, ſcripſi ambitionis cauſa: &amp; quae audiueram in Italia de moribus Papae, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalium, Epiſcoporum aliorúmque inter agreſtes &amp; inopes homines, literis in Anglia mandaui: nullum librum aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſem (Deus eſt mihi teſtis) niſi Praeſes Caſtri Londinenſis me ad ſcribendum prouocaſſet. Partim tunc temporis grandipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsione deluſus, partim appetens interituram gloriam, a me publicè ſcripta ſunt ea, praeſertim de moribus Papae, Cardina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, Epiſcoporum, totiuſque eccleſiaſtici ordinis quae fama ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceperam
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5418:16"/>à viris non fide dignis, libertate mihi eo tempore conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa paulo poſt reſipui &amp; me nequiter ſcripſiſſe Domino Lucae Kirbeo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am vita defuncto, cum in carceribus detentus fuerat, confeſſus ſum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Multa ſcripſi, multa feci, quae ſcribere aut facere negaui prorſus, antequam Praeſes Turris Londinenſis ſaepe minatus ſit, Grauiſsimum torquaris tormentum, quam acerbam poenam pati meafragilis caro abhorruit. Illius igitur inuentionem atque vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem executus ſum, quod imperabat ſcripſi, feci, ſic locutus ſum, non ex malitia, ſed ex impulſu, non ex praua voluntate, ſed ex ſatanica ſuggeſtione.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Multa ſcripſi falsò, quae ſcripſiſſe poenituit me antequam ex Anglia tanquam profugus ob enormia peccata mea quae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiae meae magnam inquietem diu &amp; noctu iniecerunt, diſceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeram, Nun quam in Anglia ſteti coram Iudice, aut alio quouis magiſtratu ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quam teſtis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra quemuis Catholicum Romanum, quando in iudicium vocati ſunt, ex propoſito abfui Londino.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Papa, Cardinales, Epiſcopi, &amp; alij Catholici Romani in me multa contulerunt beneficia, quae ingratitudine recompenſaui, ſed cauſa oſtenditur, metus grauiſsimi ſupplicij, magnifica pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa me à Deo auocauerunt. ſi vos viri digniſsimi, in eodem peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo verſaremini, neſcio quid faceretis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nihil aliud audire potui in carceribus quam has minas, Fac ſic, aut ſatellites te ducent torqueri: maluiſſem ſi dixiſſet ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendi. Non bona res eſt, corpus iſto cruciatu longius fieri per duos fere pedes quam natura concedit. Narratum eſt mihi modus torquendi, cum audiueram, timor &amp; horror iſtiuſmodi ſupplicij me omnino vicit in meaexaminatione. Quorum voluit ille Praeſes aut ſernus illius nomina ſcribi, ſcripſi. Georgius Peccam, aeques auratus in Catalogo fuit Papiſtarum, Iudex Southcotus, &amp; alij multi mihi ignoti &amp; ad nomen &amp; ad perſonam (antequam ad caſtra Londini veneram) in meo Catologo, ſuggeſtu praedictorum locum occupauerunt inter caeteros Romanae religioni addictos.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Si captus non fuiſſem cunctis Papiſtis indicaſſem interroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus me cauſam ſcribendi talia mendacia in mea examinatione. Ego fui ſcriptor, ſed Deus ſcit, alios fuiſſe autores. Si mea fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilit as me non excuſabit, appello ad miſericordiam veſtram qua munitos eſſe dicitis: oſtendite tunc illam, &amp; pro amore Dei li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate
<pb facs="tcp:5418:17"/>me, &amp; non vrgeatis me ſicut caeteri, loqui &amp; ſcribere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tr a conſcientiam meam: &amp; poſtea cernetis ſine impulſu, quod li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berè fatebor veritatem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>D. Alane grauiter te offendi, ſed tamen dico, quod recumbo in tuam clementiam. De religione nihil dico quod ſcriptura do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet (nullum excipio librum neque veteris neque noui) firmiter credo: nihil aliud credam, facite mecum quod vultis, comburite, ſuſpendite, interficite, decapitate, ego idem ſum: ſi veritatem no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habeo, Chriſtus eſt veritas, oſtendat mihi veritatem, &amp; aper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at oculos meos.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>D. Alane, Odovvenus Hoptonus Praeſes Caſtri Londinenſis minis iuſsit vt examinationem iuxta voluntatem illius ſcribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. Quando nomina Papiſtarum patefeci (quorum quam plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rima nomina nunquam ante audiueram) eos fautores Papae, Reginae Scotorum, acerrimos inimicos Regiae Maieſtatis, virorum à conciliís, &amp; omnium illorum qui defenſores ſunt religionis quae publicè in Anglia docetur aſſerere non vererer. Et omnes illi de quibus mentio facta eſt, nobiles &amp; generoſi fuerunt. Hoc ſi à te factum erit Regina promouebit te, inuenies me promptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim um fore ad te iuuandum. Cuncti proceres te magno proſequun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur amore, &amp; nihil indigebis. Mittam tecum ſeruum Oxonium, ibi ſuſtentaberis, centum Marcas ſingulis annis dabo operam vt adipiſcaris &amp; ſine dubio pingue ſacerdotium tibi dabitur. Si hoc non praeſtabis grauiſsima poena mulct aberis, conſule tibi igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Et hanc ob cauſam, partim metu ductus, partim adulatione victus, hoc in me quadrauit adagium: Quid ipſe aiebat, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maui: promiſſum illius iuramento perſtrictum fuit. Haec quae exaraui adeò vera ſunt vt nihil verius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Videte homines, qua mecum Tragedia vſus eſt ille Praeſes. Quamprimum veneram in conſpectum D. Odovveni Hopton, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus cum ſatellite, confeſſus ſum me illius religionis fuiſſe, &amp; tamen hypocriſi maxima me vti voluit, paratus eram in die Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minico iſtius hebdomadae qua captus eram in eccleſiam venire mea ſponte, &amp; tamen iuſsit vt apparerem reluctari, &amp; ſeruus illius iuſſus fuit trahere me ad eccleſiam quaſi inuitus fuiſſem: ex his paucis colligite plura.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>De bulla affix a parietibus Rhemis, hoc no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> audeo conſirmare, ſed ita fama volauit inter alummos Papae in Collegio Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cano
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5418:17"/>Romae ſito, vtrum iſta excommunicationis bulla contrae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eginam Elizabetham renouata fuit, &amp; ex integro im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſa Romae prorſus ignoro, ſed ignoſcite mihi quae tali modo te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere &amp; falſo ſcripſi &amp; feci.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quae literis mandantur, me libera ſponte ſine compulſione vlla, vt conſcientiam meam liberam redderem in praeſentia Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmi Iohnſon &amp; Georgij Robinſon mand at a ſunt in carcere Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomagenſi in die Sabbati.</hi> 19. <hi>Februarij. An.</hi> 1583.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Ioannes Nicolaus.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Octor Allen</hi> what things ſoeuer I haue written againſt the Pope, Cardinals and Biſhops, I wrote them through ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and ſuch things as I printed in England, touching the manners of the Pope, Cardinals &amp; Biſhops, I had heard them in Italie of peiſantes and poore men. I had neuer publiſhed any booke (God is my witnes) if the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the Tower of London had not prouoked me to write: for I vvas partly deluded at that time vvith great promiſes, partly alſo pricked forward with deſire of vaine glorie. Such things haue ben vvritten by me pubickly, cheefly touching the manners of the Pope. Cardinals, Biſhops, and of the vvhol Clergie, vvhich I had by report of men of no credit. But as ſone as I had obteined my libertie, incontinent I amended my former fault, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed to <hi>M. Luck Kirby</hi> novv executed, but then a priſoner, that I had vvritten very lewdly.</p>
                  <p>I wrote many things, I did many things, the which I vtterly denied either to write or to do, before that the Lieutenant of the Tovver threatened me, and that often, to rack and torment me, vvhich greuous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes my fraile fleſh did abhorre. And therefore I did but execut his vvill and inuention. Whatſoeuer he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, that I wrot, that I did, ſo I ſpake, not of mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, but by conſtraint, not of euell vvill, but of deuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb facs="tcp:5418:18"/>ſuggeſtion I vvrote many things falſly, and it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented me that euer I vvrote them before I departed out of England as a runnegate for my enormeous ſinnes, vvhich vexed and diſquieted my conſcience daie and night excedingly.</p>
                  <p>I neuer appeered before any Iudge or other officer in England as a vvitnes againſt any one Romane Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick: in ſo much that vvhen they vvere araigned, I abſented my ſelf from London of purpoſe. The Pope, the Cardinals, the Biſhops, and other Catholick Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, haue beſtovved many benefits vpon me, and I haue requited them vvith ingratitude, but I haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the cauſe: feare of greuous puniſhement and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificall promiſes withdrew me cleene from God. If you (vvorthie men) had ben in the like danger, I knovv not what you vvould haue do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. I could heare nothing els vvhiles I vvas in priſon, but theſe threates: Do ſo or els the Officers ſhal carry-thee to be racked: I had leuer he had ſaid to bee hanged. It is an euel thing to haue my bodie by theſe tortures to be made two foote longer, then euer God made it. They recompted vnto me the manner and order of racking, vvhich vvhen I heard, the feare and horror of this kinde of puniſhement did quite ouercome me in mine examination.</p>
                  <p>I vvrote dovvne into my booke the names of ſuch as the Lieutenant or his ſeruant vvould haue me write. Sir <hi>George Peckam knight</hi> vvas in the rovvle of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. <hi>Iudge Suthcot,</hi> and many other (whoſe names and perſonnes vvere vnknovvne to me before I came to the tovver) occupied a rome in my rovvle among the reſt that vvere addicted to the Roman religion, and that by the ſuggeſtion of the forenamed. If I had not ben ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, I vvould haue anſwered all Papiſts that vvould haue aſked me for vvhat cauſe I vvrote ſo many lies in my examination: That I vvas the writer in deede, but (God knovveth) other men vvere the Authors.</p>
                  <p>If my frailtie vvill not excuſe me, I appeale to your mercie: vvhere with you ſay, you are fenced: ſhevv it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5418:18"/>then, and for the loue of God ſet me at libertie, &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you ſhall ſee, that I vvill confeſſe the truth freely vvithout all conſtraint. I haue greeuouſly offended you <hi>D. Allen,</hi> yet I ſaie thus much, I do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit my ſelf wholy to your clemeneie. I ſaie nothing of my religion, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the ſcripture dooth teach (I except no booke of the old or new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) I do firmely beleeue, I beleeue no other thing. Do vvith me vvhat you liſt, burne me, ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g me, kill me, behead me: I am the ſame man, if I haue not the truth, Chriſt is the truth, let him ſhevv me the truth and open mine eies.</p>
                  <p>D. <hi>Allen,</hi> Sir <hi>Ovven Hopton</hi> the Lieutenant of the Tovver commaunded me vvith threates, to vvrite mine examination according to his will &amp; pleaſure, &amp; willed me (when I publiſhed the names of the Papiſts, many of vvhoſe names I neuer heard of before) not to be afraid to affirme them to be fautors of the Pope, of the Queene of Scots, to be mortal ennimies to the Queenes Maieſtie, to her Counſellers, &amp; to al thoſe which were defendors of the religion vvhich is novv publickly taught in England. And they vvere al noble men or gentlemen, that vvere there mentioned.</p>
                  <p>If thou vvilt do this (quoth he) the Queene vvill promote thee, and thou ſhalt find me moſt ready to helpe the: al the nobilitie vvill loue thee excedingly, and thou ſhalt vvant nothing: I vvill ſend my man with thee to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and thou ſhalt be mainteined there: I vvill find the meanes that thou ſhalt haue one hundred Marks yerely: and vvithout all doubt, thou ſhalt haue a fat benefice. If thou vvilt not do this, thou ſhalt be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and that greeuouſly: therefore take good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice vvhat to do. And for this cauſe, partly led vvith feare, &amp; partly ouercome with flatterie, the old prouerb vvas verified in me: vvhatſoeuer he did ſaie, theſame I did ſooth: al his ſaid promiſes were bound with an othe.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things that I haue vvritten are ſo true, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more true. See (ô men) hovv tragically the Lieutenant of the Tovver delt vvith me. Aſſoone
<pb facs="tcp:5418:19"/>as euer I came in Sir <hi>Ovven Hopton</hi> ſight, being brought by an officer, I confeſſed my ſelf to be of his religion, yet for al that he vvould needes haue me play the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite I vvas reddy to go to church on mine ovvne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde the next ſondaie after I vvas apprehended, yet notvvithſtanding he commaunded me to ſeeme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte, &amp; his man vvas vvilled to dravv me to the church, as though I vvent againſt my vvill: of theſe ſevv you may gather many things.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>Bull</hi> vvhich vvas faſtened vpon the vvals at <hi>Rhemes,</hi> I dare not affirme it, but there vvent ſuch a report among the Popes ſchollers in the Engliſh Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege at <hi>Rome:</hi> whether this <hi>Bull of excommunication</hi> againſt our Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> vvas renevved and printed againe at <hi>Rome,</hi> I am vtterly ignorant: but forgiue me that haue after ſuch ſort vvritten and donne, both raſhly and falſely.</p>
                  <p>Such things as I haue vvritten at this preſent, I haue vvritten them of mine ovvne free vvill vvithout any conſtraint to vnburthen my conſcience, in the preſence of <hi>VVilliam Iohnſon</hi> and <hi>George Robinſon,</hi> in the priſon of Roan, on Saterdaie being the 19. of Februarie in the yere of our Lord 1583.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Iohn Nichols.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5418:19"/>
            <p> MAKING SVTE FOR A VVARRANT TO ATTACH THE SAID IOHN NICOLS, demaund vvas made vvhether any thing could be layd to his charge ſauing matters of religion: it was anſvvered yea: and therevpon theſe articles and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations following were dravven out againſt him, vpon vvhich the priſoner being examined he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvered to euery one ſeuerally, as is here ſet downe firſt in Latine, aftervvard in Engliſh.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccuſamus Ioannem Nicolaum, primum quod famo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos libello fecerit, &amp; praelo mandauerit contra Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes &amp; publicas perſon as atque collrgia, qui famoſi libelli etiam in ditionibus ſuae Maieſtatis Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſsimae in multorummanus venerunt &amp; famam multorum le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Reſpondeo vt ſequitur. <hi>Ego Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes Nicolaus, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtans in religione,</hi> 20. <hi>Februarij anno Domini</hi> 1583. <hi>neque metu, neque fauore cuiuſquam hominis, aliquid à me reſpondebitur. Quantum ad hunc primum articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, fateor me ture recteque accuſatum eſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>In his libris, turpiſsimorum criminum mendaciter &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnioſe inſimulat nominatim certos Cardinales, obiiciens eis ſtuprum &amp; ſcelera peſsima, ex mera contra ſacrum ordinem malitia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ad ſecundum ſic reſpondeo. <hi>Fateor me ſic ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſiſſe, ſed fama atque relatione hominum prauorum, vt opinor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Sanctiſsimum Dominum noſtrum Papam ſeditiosè &amp; male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>è in iiſdem ſcriptis incuſat iniuſtitiae furti, rapinae, &amp; omnis iniquitatis, particulatim nominans quaſdam rapinas quas eum feciſſe fingit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Reſpondeo, <hi>me ſic ſcripſiſſe, ſed magis ambitionis &amp; malitiae cauſa, quam veritatis, nifi vt acceperam illum
<pb facs="tcp:5418:20"/>feciſſe aliquid quod à me literis mandatum ſit à viris illius conatibus minimè fauentibus, quod nunc non om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino à me approbatur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>In ſuis libris praedictis iniquiſsimè, &amp; (quod poſtea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſus eſt) falciſsimè accuſauit, proditionis &amp; laeſae Maieſtatis homines ſanctiſsimos, &amp; innocentiſsimos, per quod ipſius &amp; alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuorum complicum falciſſimum teſtimonium, plurimi, id eſt</hi> 12 <hi>religioſiſsimi viri aut plures fuerunt crudeliſsima morte ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lati. Eumque interrogari cupimus, an aliorum inductione vel ſua ſola malitia, eos falsò accuſauerit, &amp; qui eum induxerunt ad hoc.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ad quartum ſic reſpondeo. <hi>Me ſemper negaſse ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod teſtimonium in ducturum contra quemcunque ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem qui ob religionem paſſus eſt: ſed in libris meis inſinuaui, quod multi in Collegio Anglicano Romae ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o, optauerunt mortem Reginae, &amp; multorum aliorum vt ſcribitur iſto libro: &amp; in illo articulo addidi plus quam veritas conceſsit. Et quantum ad nomina illuſtriſsimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum virorum, vt nomen Domini</hi> Leiceſtriae, <hi>vt nomen Domini</hi> Burleighi, <hi>Reginae conquaeſtoris, Domini</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſci Vvalzingham &amp;c. <hi>quos viros neque accuſatos, neque minatos ab aliquo in iſto Collegio audiui, ſed hoe ambitionis &amp; lucri cauſa finxi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 <hi>Accuſauit mendaciter &amp; malitiosè Anglorum Collegium (ſuae Maieſtatis fauore Rhemis reſidens) quod Bullam Pij V. contra Reginam Angliae datam, Rhemis publicauerit, &amp; valuis &amp; poſtibus illius vrbis affixerit, ex quo iniquiſsimo mendacio, &amp; calumnia, illius collegij alumni, magnam poſteà incurrerunt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginae ſuae indignationem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ad quintum articulum <hi>ſic reſpondeo. Quod iunio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſtudentes retulerunt mihi quod Bulla anaihematis per Pium V. facta contra Reginam noſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Elizabetham, renouata fuit per Gregorium Papam XIII. &amp; retu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerunt mihi quod illa Bullae Pij V. publicata fuit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis &amp; valuis &amp; poſtibus illius vrbis affixa. Hoc leui
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5418:20"/>illorum relatione ſcripſi: ſed hac dere, non melius ſciui, quam infans vnius diei, quia Rhemis tunc temporis non fui.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6 <hi>Nuper etiam in Galliis exiſtens ſcripſit ante</hi> 10. <hi>dies, aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas literas ad quendam grauem virum, in quibus famam &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem Collegij Anglorum multiplici mendacio, conuitio, calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, &amp; detractione grauiſsima, laeſit: dicens praedictum Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium docere &amp; committere omnia mala, &amp; quod viderit oculis ſuis continuo in Collegio fieri quae nimis ſunt dictu turpia &amp; hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda, vt ita falciſsima calumnia &amp; patres ſocietatis Ieſu, qui illud Collegium Romae regunt, &amp; ipſorum diſcipulos collegij a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnos infamia notari.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Quantum ad ſextum, <hi>hoc reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deo. Iſtiuſmodi lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras ſcripſi, ſed ſuperbia, &amp; animus cupiens in Anglia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueri, ad ſcribendum me duxit. Et quantum ad Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium</hi> Rhemenſe, <hi>hoc dico: quod plus ex malitia, quam ex veritate dixi. &amp; ſic alterum Collegium quod eſt</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae <hi>falsò à me accuſatum eſt. Et de Doctore</hi> Alano, <hi>in conſcientialoquor, nihil aliud ſcio aut audiui quam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentiam, ſua religione excepta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7 <hi>Praeteriſta, periurij crimen ipſum incurriſſe, probabimus. non ſolum ex eo, quod poſt publicam, ſolemnem &amp; voluntariam haereſeon abiurationem Romae ante quadriennium factam, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſus ſit in abiuratas haereſes: ſed ex eo quod interpoſito tureiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando promiſerit (cum Collegij Romani alumnus eſſet) ſe ſuſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturum ſacros ordines, &amp; in Angliam profecturu ad propagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum fidem Catholicam, quandocunque à ſuperioribus id eſſet ſibi mandatum. Quod promiſſum iureiurando confirmatum, iam ipſe eum ing enti ſcandalo irritum fecit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ad ſeptimum articulum reſpondeo. <hi>Illum arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum eſſe verum, &amp; incurri periurium, quia</hi> Romae <hi>vixi vt hypocrita, nunquam exiſtens in religione Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae Romana, praeſertim corde.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8 <hi>Porro, obiicimus illi, quod Pontificem dolo male frauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerit,
<pb facs="tcp:5418:21"/>quando ſub pretextu aduerſae valetudinis, &amp; quod aërem Romanum ferre non potuerit, petiit à ſua Sanctitate veniam eundi ad Collegium Rhemenſe, vt ibi ſtudia proſequeretur, &amp; ſacerdotium ſuſciperet, in eum finem poſtulans &amp; accipiens à ſua Sanctitate</hi> 50. <hi>aureos, cum ille accepta per fraudem hac pecunia recte profectus eſt in Angliam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ad octauum articulum reſpondeo, <hi>me defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſſe Papam</hi> 25. <hi>aureor um, quos mihi dedit in via via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tici vt</hi> Rhemos <hi>peruenirem, ſed</hi> Rhemos <hi>non veni, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta in</hi> Angliam <hi>profectus ſum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ob omnes praedictos articulos ſic à me</hi> Ioanne Nicolao <hi>conceſſos dolor magnus me tenet, &amp; ſub pedibus cuiuſque quem ſic malitiosè &amp; grauiter offendi, me ipſum proſterno &amp; ſubiicio. Deus ſcit, animo euadendi fortunatus promotionibus, quam deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derio veritatem loquendi ductus. Deus ſit mihi miſericors, &amp; propitius, &amp; ignoſcat mihi pariter cum illis quos ſic temere &amp; impieo ffendi. Peto vt omnes illi qui per me offenſi ſunt, pro amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Chriſti, tantae iniuriae immerito illis illatae, obliuiſcantur. partim hanc tetigi culpam Satanae ſuggeſtu, &amp; partim quod multilaudauerunt ea quae ſic impudenter ſcripſeram.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Per me Ioannem Nicolaum Anglum.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee doo accuſe Iohn Nicols, firſt, for that he made infamous libels, and ſet them downe in print, againſt Princes, publicks perſones, and Colledges: vvhich infamous libels came to the handes of many in his moſt Chriſtian Maieſties Dominions, and haue ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed the good name of many a man.</p>
                  <p>I Iohn Nicols Proteſtant, the xx. of February <hi>An. Domini</hi> 1583. doo anſwere as followeth: That I meane to do nothing for feare nor fauor as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5418:21"/>touching the firſt article, I confeſſe that it is a truth that I am accuſed of.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 In theſe bookes he doth accuſe falſely and ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly many Cardinals by name, of moſt filthie crimes, obiecting vnto them vvhoredonne, and moſt wicked acts, and that of meere mallice againſt the ſacred fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                  <p>As touching the ſecond, I confeſſe that I wrot ſo, but vpon the report of levvde perſons.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 In the ſame vvritings, he dooth accuſe ſediciouſly and reprochfully the Popes holynes of iniuſtice, theſte, roberye, and al iniquitie, naming certen roberies parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, vvhich he hath fained him to commit.</p>
                  <p>To the third article I agree, that I haue written ſo, but of ambition and mallice: but euen as I haue receiued (by reporte that the Pope did ſomevvhat as is vvritten of him by me) of men that ſauored not his proceedings: which things aftervvard vpon better aduiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, I did not, nor do allovve.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 In his foreſaid bookes he hath accuſed moſt holy and innocent men, moſt vniuſtly and (as him ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed aftervvards) moſt falſely, of treaſon and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie againſt their princes perſone: ſo that through his, and his companions falſe witnes: many, that is to ſaie, xij. moſt religious men or more, were put to moſt cruel death. And vve deſire you to enquire of him, vvhether he falſly accuſed them of his ovvne mallice, or induced therevnto by others, and vvhat they vvere that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto induced him?</p>
                  <p>To the fourth thus I anſwere: that I alvvaies denied to bring forth any euidence againſt any one perſone that ſuffered in England for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion:
<pb facs="tcp:5418:22"/>but I inſinuated in my booke that diuers in the College at Rome, vviſhed the death of the Queene and diuers others as is ſpecified in that booke. and in that article I added more then truth is. And as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the names of honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſonages, as my Lord of <hi>Leyceſter,</hi> my Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> Sir <hi>Frauncys Vvalzingham</hi> &amp;c. which men I neuer heard accuſed or threatened, by any of the College, but vvere for ambition and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerment ſake forged.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 He hath falſly and maliciouſly accuſed the Engliſh College (now by his maieſties fauor reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Rhemes) that they did publiſh in Rhemes the Bull that Pius V. ſet forth againſt the Queene of England: and that they did faſten it vpon the gates and vvals of that citie: by occaſion of which wicked lye &amp; ſlaunder, the ſtudentes of that College, did incure the highe indignation of their Queene.</p>
                  <p>As touching the fifth article, this I ſaie: that by light reporte of the yonger ſtudentes, I reported in my booke that the <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Pius V.</hi> was renued by the Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the thirteenth, &amp; vvas fixed vpon the poſts at <hi>Rhemes,</hi> vvhich thing I knew aſvvel as the infant of one daies age.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 And novv of late being here in Fraunce, he vvrote not ten daies ſince, open letters to a certain graue man: in vvhich letters he did vvith many a lie, reproche, ſlaunder, and greeuous detraction, empaire the good fame and honor of the Engliſh College: ſaying that the foreſaid College dooth teach and commit al euels, and that he hath ſeene vvith his eies that to be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in that college, which are horrible things, &amp; to filthie to be ſpoken, ſo that by this moſt falſe ſlaunder, he dooth defame, both the fathers of the ſocietie of Ieſus, vvhich gouuerne that College at Rome, as alſo their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5418:22"/>ſchollers the ſtudentes of that colledge.</p>
                  <p>As touching the ſixth article, this I anſvvere, that I wrote ſuch a letter, but of pride, &amp; a minde to be preferred in England. And as touching the College of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> this I ſaie, that I ſpake more of mallice then of truth: and ſo in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe the College of <hi>Rome</hi> vvas falſely accuſed by me. And as concerning <hi>M. Doctor Allen,</hi> I ſay in conſcience, that I knovv or haue heard by the man nothing els but innocencie, his religion excepted.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Beſides theſe vve vvill proue him to be a periured perſon, not onely for that he is in relapſe, &amp; falne againe into thoſe hereſies, vvhich he abiured publickly, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely, &amp; voluntarily at Rome 4. yeres ſince: but for that he promiſed vpon his othe (when he was a ſtudent in the Engliſh College at Rome) that he vvould take holy orders, and go into England, and there to teach the Catholick faith vvhenſoeuer he ſhould be ſent by his ſuperiors. which promis (confirmed vvith an oth) he hath broken, not vvithout great ſcandall.</p>
                  <p>The ſeuenth article is true: and I haue incurred periurie, for that at Rome I liued as an hypocrite, being neuer in hart of the Romane religion.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Moreouer vve obiect to him, that he abuſed the Pope vvith craft and deceipt, vvhen vnder pretence of ſicknes, and that he could not awaie vvith the aier of Rome, he deſired leaue of his holynes to come to the College at Rhemes, there to follow his ſtudie, and to be made prieſte, and to that ende requeſting and receiuing of his holynes 50. crovvnes of gold, but aſſoone as he had gotten the money thus fraudently, he vvent ſtraight into England.</p>
                  <p>As concerning the eight article it is graunted, I defrauded the Pope of 25. crownes giuen vnto
<pb facs="tcp:5418:23"/>me in vvay of <hi>Viaticum</hi> to bing me to Rhemes.</p>
                  <p>For al theſe articles being thus graunted by me <hi>Iohn Nicols,</hi> I am right ſory, and ſubmit me ſelf vnder the feete of any ſuch as I haue maliciouſly and greuouſly offended. God knovveth I ſpake theſe things vvith a deſire to be promoted, rather then vvith a minde to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the truth. God be merciful vnto me and pardon me, and al thoſe vvhom I haue thus offended vvilfully I crie mercie: and beſeech them for Chriſt his ſake to forget ſuch iniuries ſo impudently committed againſt them, partly by Sathans prompting, partly by the countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of others in commending ſuch ſtuf.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>By me <hi>Iohn Nicols</hi> Engliſhman.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="document">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>M. Stubs</hi> gaue me the matter of my booke in the Tovver, intituled: <hi>The recantion of Iohn Nicols, &amp;c.</hi> M. <hi>Vvilkinſon</hi> did vvrite in the margent the notes: and alſo added to that vvhich I vvrote, and corrected the faults by me eſcaped.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer I told my <hi>Lord Treſeurer</hi> about alhallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide laſt paſt <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1582. theſe vvordes that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovve: <hi>If it may pleas your honor, I am right ſorie that I haue ſuch bookes put forth, that conteine more falſehood then truth.</hi> My lord anſvvered, that the Papiſt found out that I lyed.</p>
                  <p>Vvhen I confeſſed to <hi>M. Kirkby</hi> in the tovver that it repented me in vvriting ſuch bookes as vvere contrary to the truth, <hi>M. Lucas Kirkby</hi> reported theſe my vvords to <hi>M. Reignolds</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> vvho made reporte thereof to <hi>Sir Frauncys Vvalzingham</hi> vvho being certified of this thing vvrote or ſent to <hi>M. Lieutenant</hi> of the Tovver of London, that I ſhould be ſent for, and examined face to face before <hi>M. Kirkby</hi> to knovv vvhether it vvas ſo or not as <hi>Sir Frauncis</hi> vvas certified. Vvhen I came to the Tovver, <hi>M. Kirkby</hi> vſed theſe vvordes to me vvhen he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5418:23"/>ſaw me. <hi>Speke the truth</hi> (quoth he) <hi>and ſhame the Diuel.</hi> So I vvill (quoth I) doubte not thereof: <hi>M. Kirkby</hi> was examined apart, and I anſvvered truly, if I had been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by <hi>M. Lieutenant</hi> ſo to do. For vvhen I ſaid ſo, <hi>I told M. Kirkby that I vvrote thoſe bookes for ambition,</hi> ſay not ſo (quoth M. Lieutenant) vvrite (quoth he to his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary) after this manner: <hi>That he vvas ſorie that he vvrot his bookes ſo rudely as he did.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vvhen <hi>M Reignolds</hi> in the preſence of Doctor <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> told me that he vvould proue to my face before M. Doctor <hi>Humfrey (M. Kirkby</hi> being called before them) that I had vttered ſuch vvords, as that I vvas ſorie that my bookes were publiſhed conteinning more vntruth then veritie, and that I ſaid I vvould forge no more againſt the Papiſts neither in print nor pulpit. Vvhich thing vvhen M. <hi>Lieutenant</hi> heard, he had him hold his peace. and talke no more thereof.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>By me <hi>Iohn Nicols.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:5418:24"/>
            <head>THE SATISFACTION. OF LAV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RENCE CADDEY, TOVCHING <hi>his frailties, and fall from the Catholike Church, at his retorne into England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F there be any Catholicks in England or out of England, that heard of my ſpeach or recantation at Paules croſſe, which was in the yere of our Lord 1581. Theſe are to certifie them that it vvas directly againſt my conſcience, and that I vvas neuer of that Religion that then I pretended, as God ſhal ſaue me at the general day of Iudgement.</p>
            <p>For I will ſhew plainely and manifeſtly that of my inward defection from our Mother the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> there were neuer any effectual cauſes, vvhereby it may moſt cleerely appeere that invvardly I vvas neuer ſince my firſt reconciliation to the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. For either I invvardly ſeparated my ſelf from the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> becauſe I thought ſome points of the Churches doctrine to be falſe, or for the euel life of the Catholicks.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, although I neuer ſtudied diuinitie, but as much as ſome Cathecumini do, and the yonger ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers that are yet in the courſe of Philoſophie, or other prophane ſciences, yet I am not (I thanke God) ſo dull of vvit, but I can Iudge ſomewhat of Religion and of the difference betwene the <hi>Catholicks</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> by the ſermons of learned men which I haue here to fore frequented, by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation I had vvith learned Fathers, vvhich daily did expound the harder points of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5418:24"/>Religion, and often did diſſolue diuers foliſh and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Sophiſmes of hereticks.</p>
            <p>Whereby I knovv, and truly euer ſince my firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion did knovv, that euery point of the <hi>Catholick religion</hi> is conformable to the vvord of God, although the hereticks do falſely ſay that they are grounded vpon the bare traditions of men: and to me it is euident that there is no article of the <hi>Catholick faith</hi> novv called in doubt, which may not be proued by diuers places of the ſcriptures, or by moſt cleere ſequell inuincebly deduced and gathered of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And where the aduerſaries ſay, that either the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks do recite places out of the ſcriptures, vvhich are not authe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tical, or els if they do allege places out of the true ſcriptures that they expound them falſely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ovvne fancies, I vvas neuer ſince my firſt reconcilement ſo ſimple or necligent of my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as not to ſee, that to be an vſual ſtale euaſion of al old hereticks.</p>
            <p>For this I knovv, that <hi>Luther</hi> that provvde Lucifers <hi>Primogenitus,</hi> or vvhat other ſingular ſectarie ſoeuer, being but one man, although he had ben moſt holy in the ſight of men, as in deede he vvas moſt vnholy and vvicked both before God and man, ought not to iudge ſcriptures to be authentical or not authentical by his owne priuate, vnconſtant and variable ſpirit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the Iudgement of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>General Councel</hi> vvhich determineth ſuch things by the ſpirit of truth, promiſed by Chriſts expreſſe vvord, and ſo cleerely te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in ſcriptures, to abide vvith the ſame to th'end of the vvorld.</p>
            <p>And in truth, it vvas a note ſure enough for me to confirme my ſelf in my forefathers faith and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne in my conſcience the contrary ſect of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, that I heard by men of full credit (howſoeuer th'Engliſh ſectaries vvrith and vvrangled in the matter of late to ſaue their honeſties) that one heretick, as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> by his ſpirit denieth ſome bookes that our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts
<pb facs="tcp:5418:25"/>accept to be Gods word by the iudgement of their ſpirit. and I ſavv it plainely by mine owne late experience of them, that they receiue and condemne, admit or repell, euen as they thinke good for the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the cauſe, and as may beſt ſerue for the defence of their deuelliſh doctrine. Wherein truly (I ſay for the reuerend reſpect and honotable dealing with the diuine booke of Gods word) not withſtanding the aduerſaries pretending al reuerence towards the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and tedious vaunting, talking, and toſſing of them, the Catholicks yet do ſo farre paſſe them in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious keeping, preſeruing, interpreting, tranſlating, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaging, &amp; al other vſe of holy vvrit, as the true owner and occuper of any thing, paſſeth the theefe and vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. I beleeue it, and haue had experience of it in both ſides, and therefore I ſpeake it.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, that is, th'expoſition of ſcriptures, I knew it was the property of al hereticks to abuſe, wreſt and vvring them, to vvhatſoeuer them ſelues liſt, and particularly to the priuate ſence of euery ſecte maiſter, ech one for his owne erronious doctrine and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of his fellowes. I haue heard vvith mine owne eares, and ſeene vvith mine owne eyes: that the ſcriptures ſound al for <hi>Luther</hi> and againſt the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries in Germany: and in England and ſome other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, al the Bible is at <hi>Caluins</hi> and <hi>Bezas</hi> beck, and ſoundeth vvhatſoeuer they ſay, againſt not onely the <hi>Catholicks</hi> or <hi>Lutheranes,</hi> but againſt their ovvne booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon praier, actes and iniunctions publiſhed by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: the Puritanes there hauing reconced aboue an hundreth and ſortie errors in th'Engliſh ſeruice againſt the ſcriptures, &amp; vvhich I noted in the time of my being in England eſpecially in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> aſwel the writers, Preachers, Readers and Diſputers, as moſt other ſchollers and prentiſes be puritanes, condemning by Gods word that ſame ſeruice &amp; adminiſtration vvhich them ſelues daily reſort vnto.</p>
            <p>For vvhich who ſoeuer ſhall reade the writings of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5418:25"/>
               <hi>M. Vvhittakers,</hi> or the diſputes of <hi>Fulke, Charke, Vvalker,</hi> and ſuch other Miniſters lately had in the Tower, they ſhal find my vvords and obſeruation true, and ſhall ſee many points of puritaniſme decided by them by coulor of ſcriptures, againſt their ovvne authorized ſeruice, &amp; all thoſe things ſet out by authoritie.</p>
            <p>I neede not ſtand to tell you now the <hi>Lutheranes</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound this notorious text, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> ſo farre othervviſe then the <hi>Zuinglians</hi> and <hi>Caluiniſts,</hi> that they haue prooued theſe, by Gods expreſſe vvord hereticks: and theſe, them for the reciproke, plaine carnal men and Idolaters: both th'one and th'other vvrithing the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred words to their owne erronious and damnable ſect againſt the proper nature and plaine ſenſe, vvhich the letter, the circumſtance, the conference of places, the auncient fathers, Councels, and the vvhole Church ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſetteth downe. Vvith this I haue marked that the Sectaries of our countrey and al other places, being ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, vaine-glorious, louers of them ſelues, and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſers of their ovvne fantaſies, ſeeke for nothing but nouelties, and in th'expoſition of ſcriptures to finde out that which neuer neither foole nor wiſeman found out before them, and al this vvith a ridiculous boaſt of euery mans ſeuerall ſpirit, gifte and knowledge, vvhich to me and others that ſee their liues and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and partly know their intention, is a ſtraunge caſe.</p>
            <p>Hovv ſoeuer it be, their expoſition ſo nevv, ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, ſo inconſtant, ſo various, ſo farre differing from the comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taries of al the fathers, paſſing al theſe men in al grace and knowlege, from the general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, that not by particular fanſie of a few, but by vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme conſent of the moſt learned in the vvorld, haue by Gods vvord (truly through th'aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt vnderſtood) defined theſe things to our hands: this conſideration I ſay of their vngodly behauiour towards the holy ſcriptures, the glorious Doctors, &amp; the vniuerſall Church of al ages and nations, of which
<pb facs="tcp:5418:26"/>by my late being among them, I haue enformed my ſelf better then euer I could haue do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne by reading of bokes or here ſay, hath fortified my faith againſt them, I truſt in God, during life. But becauſe I profeſſe not in this breif ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to diſpute of the matter, or arrogate to my ſelf any profound knowlege in theſe things, I for this point ſay no more but this, that if I had ben partly bent to hereſie when I vvent into Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as I was not (I ſpeake it as before God) the more I had ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant with the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, yea with the learnedſts amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſoner ſhould I haue ben reclaimed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hereſie.</p>
            <p>For in other things though I may bouldly ſaie they haue the gifts of the mind as plentifully as any nation, yet in diuinitie &amp; ſpecially in theſe controuerſies, they are ſo bewitched, that through the common malady of hereſie, vvhich by Gods iuſt iudgement of ſinne and for ſaking th'obedience of his Church, is euer ioyned vvith pitifull darkenes of vnderſtanding, eſpecially in ſuch as brag moſt of the light, that when they bring but <hi>Sophiſmes</hi> to proue their religion, they both thinke and bouldly aduouch, that they are demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrations. But here they wil exclaime after their manner and ſay they bring places of ſcripture, &amp; wil charge me that I cal the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <hi>Sophiſmes.</hi> No God forbid, for that were blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, but I call the falſe and childiſh expoſition, or the place (either by falſe tranſlation or expoſition wreſted) a Sophiſme, the vvhich may ſone be eſpied of him that hath any iudgement or common ſenſe, eſpecially if God hath lightened his vnderſtanding by the doctrine of the <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, if I had fauored hereſies, this would haue reuoked me, to ſee ſome of thoſe that on this ſide the ſcas were both counted &amp; know to be void of all good gifts and qualities of the minde, not capable of any ſcience, yet at their retorne home, to be admitted to be publick preachers, and their vvords, being nothing but knowne forgeries &amp; blaſphemous lyes, to be compted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Oracles and concluſions deduced out of th'expreſſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5418:26"/>vvord of the Lord, as they ſpeke in our countrey.</p>
            <p>One ſaith very vviſely of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that he vſed hard and difficult termes in Philoſophie to driue awaie from the reading of his bookes thoſe that vvere ſimple and vnlearned, leſt ſaith he, <hi>Omnia harpiarum more immundo contactu conſpurcarent:</hi> that is to ſay: leſt they ſhould diminiſh and abaſe the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maieſtie of philoſophie by their fooliſh and doting expoſitions. How ſoeuer it is in that facultie of Philoſophie, ſure it is, that the written vvord of God is full of profound myſteries, &amp; yet is confidently, bouldly and malepertly expounded now in England, as vvel priuatly at euery table and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, as in the pulpits and common aſſemblies of ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and vnlearned artificers, ſo that the lay people, pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes eſpecially and yong ſchollers, aſſone as they can bid Caeſar good morrow in Greeke, or reade th'Engliſh Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yea the women dare preſume to diſpute with the Clergie of the cheefeſt points of Religion, and bouldly condemne the cheefeſt clercks in the vvorld.</p>
            <p>Is not this I pray you a great abaſing of th'excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of the vvord of God? ſurely if I had fauored hereſies: this would haue ben a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t motiue to haue reuoked me. I could bring many moe ſtrong reaſons to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but becauſe I am a yong nouice in learning, and becauſe I thinke this vvhich I haue brought will ſuffice to proue that there vvas no cauſe of my invvard defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in reſpect of my particular knowledge, I vvil here end this firſt point.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, that I had no cauſe to ſeperate my ſelf from the <hi>Catholick church</hi> for the euel life of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, and to come to be a Proteſtant for their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, I vvil ſhew it manifeſtly, and yet no great profe vvil be loked for at my hands therein. Firſt, ſuppoſe the Catholicks liued very euel, &amp; as ill as their aduerſaries (purpoſely to deceiue the people) faine them to do, if I thinke the Religion to be good, their euel life ſhould neuer cauſe me to for ſake it, if a man ſhould meaſure truth &amp; faith by the elle of vertu and innocencie in the
<pb facs="tcp:5418:27"/>profeſſors &amp; follovvers of any ſort, in mans frailtie &amp; miſerie of this life, God ſhould haue no people nor part in this world al being ſubiect to ſin and danger in this mortal ſtate. But ſurely if wee ſhould docide the matter by the difference of life, behauiour, and conuerſation of both ſides, I vvere vvorſe then an aſſe to determine for the Proteſtants againſt the Catholicks, amongeſt whom the firſt Profeſſors vvere Saincts, and the cheef leaders and teachers aftervvard moſt holy, and al theſe follovvers though fraile and ſinfull men, yet finding remedy by the medicinable Sacraments, penaunce and diſcipline of the Church, for their daily offences.</p>
            <p>Where contrary vviſe the very firſt authors of this Proteſtancy, <hi>Luther, Caluin, Beza</hi> and the like, or as them ſelues call them, the reſtorers &amp; reformers of Religion, vvere not onely vulgarly nought, but of notorious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous wicked life: as their Miniſters be in al cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treies, and their zelous followers not good in any place, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, where they haue notoriouſly betraied their falſe faith, by their foule fruicts. Yea and vvhere it is knowne that their doctrine it ſelf, hath ſó altered to the vvorſe al kinde of States: and that their pulpits are nothing els but a ſchoole of ſinne, licentiouſnes, luſt and liberty, that al wiſemen wonder at it, and good men lament the caſe.</p>
            <p>Who knoweth not that vertue, deuotion, &amp; godly life it ſelf is bourthenous and hateful to the Proteſtants, ſo far ſurely that they ſeeke as I haue ſeene not onely to aboliſh, deface; and deſtroy, the bookes now or of ould written for defence and proofe of the Catholick faith, which they may do vpon ſome pretence of errors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in the ſame, but they burne vp al godly treatiſes and bookes of contemplation, meditation, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſtian life and manners, conteining no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of religion at al, as long ſith they vſed a deuout treatiſe, <hi>of the life and Immitation of Chriſt:</hi> and now of late they openly burned a number of the bookes <hi>of prayer</hi> and <hi>meditation of prayer</hi> made by <hi>Levves of Granado</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5418:27"/>together with the new Teſtament. Aſſure your ſelues that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not abide ſuch bookes of al others, knowing that deuout praier onely, penaunce and amendement of life, vvill eaſily bring men from their prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in which no ſuch deuotions are found. Neither, if you marke vvell, ſhall you euer finde that the learned of the Proteſtants writ or treat of any ſuch argument, al their doings are in <hi>pugnis verborum,</hi> in ſtrife, emulation, contention, contradiction, deſtruction. They ſtand vpon quick diſpatch, and attribute al to Chriſt his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, without ether much meditation of it, or confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them ſelues vnto it. Finally they haue turned the grace of Chriſt into carnal luſt and licence.</p>
            <p>To ſee theſe things which in England are ſo open and euident, not ſo much profound learning is requiſite, as due conſideration, and ſome experience of other places, vvhich if our Gentlemen, ſtudents and others, ether of the ynnes of Court or vniuerſities, or of what other place or calling ſoeuer might haue: as diuers by trauelling ouer the ſeas to ether of the Seminaries or other Catholick ſchooles haue happely proued, they ſhould ſee vvhat difference of life, manners, education, and behauiour there is betwixt the one and th'other.</p>
            <p>This one thing I dare be bould to ſay, for the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of <hi>Rome,</hi> where I moſt liued in mine abſence from my countrey which therefore I knew beſt, and vvhich the vvicked calumniators haue moſt ſought to ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, the youthes and ſtudents al, there, be as vertuous as any be in Chriſtendome. And let both <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambrige,</hi> giue me one ſuch for hollynes of life and conuerſation (ſo long as they be there vnder the Proteſtants regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) as there be a number in the ſaid Seminary, and I promis you I vvill ſay in <hi>S. Peters</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> al that I ſaid at <hi>Paules croſſe</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not vvithſtanding (as I ſaid) al euel life maketh not nor proueth one to be an heretick, for I am an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor as other men, and perhaps the cheef of many ſinners, but I haue found remedy, mercie &amp; ſaluation, in
<pb facs="tcp:5418:28"/>the Church, in vvhich onely the holie Paſſion of Chriſt the cauſe of al remiſſion, is profitable, and out of the ſame, nothing but damnation though mans life ſeeme neuer ſo iuſte and holy. For this his bleſſed paſſions ſake I truſt he vvill nether now remember the ſinnes of my youth nor this my exterior reuolt from his holy Church, vvhich I profeſſe as before to haue ben of frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie againſt mine owne conſcience and knowlege. God that knoweth al things, knoweth that I did it not for any liking I had of the Proteſtants either life or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, knowing both to be ſtarke nought, onely the Diuel by falſe and ſubtil perſuaſions vvas the cauſe of my outward defection. Firſt I had a ſeruent deſire to ſee my parents and freends, and becauſe I vvas afraid, they neither durſt nor vvould receiue me for ſeare of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuts. I thought it good to play the hypocrite (if that may be called hypocriſie, to put on the habit and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of wickednes) with the <hi>Biſhop of London,</hi> that is, to faine my ſelf to be an heretick, that thereby I might procure his licence, and ſo goe to my freends both without their danger &amp; mine owne. The Biſhop being a wily Fox ſtraight waies commaunded me to ſignifie ſo much in publick audience, and then he vvould graunt me my requeſt, then beganne the tragedie of my vvo &amp; miſerie.</p>
            <p>I began to excuſe my ſelf of fearefulnes, &amp; to wepe before him that taught the Biſhops ſonnes, and befote <hi>Iohn Dias</hi> the Biſhops chaplen. Then I thought vvith my ſelf, that if I ſhould withſtand the Biſhop, a thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worldly inconueniences ſhould haue enſued the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof, becauſe I had ſaid before, I vvas as he vvas in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, theſe and other ſuch like cauſes of my miſerable outward defection did the Diuel put into my hed: who although he had thought to haue throwne me downe for euer at that time, yet I hope to giue him and al his the ouerthrow, and neuer here after vvhile I liue to yeld to ſuch like temptations, for the performaunce vvhereof, I beſeech the <hi>bleſſed virgin Marie,</hi> and al the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5418:28"/>holy company of heauen, and al good Catholicks to pray for me. I could name ſome vvitneſſes of the great paſſions and in ward ſtrife I had vvith my ſelf vpon the firſt conſideration of my pretended reuoult, but that I dare not name them for putting the godly men in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: this onely I vvil ade therein, that al the world may ſee I neuer vvas theirs in hart ſith my firſt reconcileme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt when I was in priſon in the <hi>Gatehorrſe,</hi> I went euery daie to the dore of a Catholick which lay in the next rome to the chamber I lay in, &amp; weeping bitterly, ſhevved him that I ſhould do againſt my conſcience, from vvhich he merueilous charitably and comfortably dehorted me, vvith great reaſons and incouragement to be conſtant in confeſſion of my faith: but the Diuel, his Miniſters, and mine infirmitie preuailed, and I did that vvhich was required at my hands. After I had done that which euer ſince hath ben a naile in my conſcience, in diuers places I vvas conuerſant vvith the Catholicks, and neuer vttered or hurt any, nor vvould haue done for al the good in the vvorld, the perſons and places I could name but for their endangering.</p>
            <p>When I vvas at <hi>Cambrige,</hi> I counſelled diuers to go ouer ſea, and perſuaded them ſo, that I had brought them ouer vvith me in deede, if it had not ben for feare of their Tutors-Many youthes there be (God be thanked for it) vvel bent to vertu and the <hi>Catholick Religion,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God bring them thence. Beſides, vvhen my cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber fellowes eſpecially, one <hi>Sir Hutton,</hi> Doctor <hi>Hutton</hi> his nephevv, vvould ſpeke againſt <hi>F. Campion,</hi> I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him ſo farre, that he called me often Papiſt, and defendor of Traitors, and threatened he vvould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of me to the Maiſter and the Seniors. I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſame, and hovv he vvas falſely accuſed, &amp;c. in mine ovvne countrey to one, being both vvell learned and very catholickly bent as vvee vvalked by the Seas ſide.</p>
            <p>But ſome vvil obiect I kept company vvith <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5418:29"/>Nichols,</hi> a feruent heretick: to vvhich Obiection I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvere, confeſſing that I kept him company to much, for if I had follovved him in al points, he vvould haue brought both him ſelf and me to euerlaſting deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: for I am ſure, that neuer vvoman brought out ſuch a horrible and ougley monſter in manners as he is. But if ye conſider th'end vvherefore I vvas conuerſant vvith him, I hope ye vvill not thinke me to be much blame vvorthie.</p>
            <p>Firſt I vvent about to knovv his lying ſpirite and his deteſtable manners, vvhich I am ſure I knovv (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though to mine owne diſcredit) as vvell as any: but eſpecially I vvent about to get him out of England, from being the cauſe of ſhedding of Innocent blood, the vvhich I thanke God I haue obteined, &amp; haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured his apprehenſion, not for hatred or hurt of his perſon, as God dooth knovv, but for deſire of ſauing his ſoule, and detections of his foule ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders againſt the Church of God and her children. I vvas neuer (I thanke God, moſt humbly) of his malitious humor, if I had ben, I might haue vomited my poiſon againſt the Catholicks, I might haue gone to the priuie counſel, &amp; haue enſtauled my ſelf as many do, I might haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued good conditions of liuing being offred, I might haue ſtaide at <hi>Cambrige</hi> at the coſt of my parents vvhich are able to keepe me in the ſchooles of learning: many commodious vvaies for vvorldly preferment I might haue follovved, if I had invvardly liked of that foule hereſie, nether had I any neede to go into a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, vvhere <hi>I</hi> knevv, I ſhould liue poorely.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, vvhiles I was in England this laſt time, I vvas neuer quiet in conſcience, becauſe vvhatſoeuer I did, I did it againſt the ſame. Other reaſons I could yeld, but becauſe I vvilbe ſhort, theſe ſhal ſuffice: one thing doth comfort me no litle, that many haue falne as groſely as I haue donne, and aftervvards haue become moſt firme and conſtant. It remaineth onely, that for this publick ſinne and ſcandal, and al other offences, I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5418:29"/>craue pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, of the holy Church, of Chriſt his Vicar here vpon earth <hi>Gregory the XIII.</hi> of that name, head of the ſaid holy Church, and al other that I gaue ſcandall to thereby. And I requeſt al good Catholicks to take me as their brother in Chriſt Ieſu. And I beſeech al good Chriſtians for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake to pray for me, that I neuer become an heretick, but that I may liue and die in the Catholick and Apoſtolick Church, which is the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and that after this life I may enioy the kingdom of heauen: to the vvhich God bring vs for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, to vvhom vvith the Father &amp; the holy Ghoſt, be al honor, power, and glory, both now and for euer world without end.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Laus Deo ac deiparae virgini Mariae.</hi> 
               <signed>By me Laurence Caddey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>THE COPIE OF A LETTER <hi>vvritten by the ſaid Laurence Caddey, to his Patron and frend.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thinke my ſelf happy moſt worthy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron that your Fatherly affection towards me is not decreaſed, but wonderfully and more then I could looke for, augmented. I now ſee that firſt of al you haue a great loue to my ſoule, ſecondarily to your Countrey and to me your poore countrey-man, a great thing it is to beſtowe vpon me my habit, but vvhat greater then to giue your vvord, and beſides a teſtimoniall moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie in theſe perillous times, but you can do no other ſeing that the quallities of the trevv Church be in you <hi>eminentiſsimo quodam modo,</hi> the vvhich moſt aboundantly dooth beſtow not onely <hi>interna Chariſmata,</hi> vpon thoſe that penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly doo runne vnto her for ſoccour: but alſo al exteriour graces neceſſary for them, you therfore be
<pb facs="tcp:5418:30"/>no ſtepfather nor ſhee no ſtepmother, but moſt louing and charitable nouriſhers both of the invvard and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, of your penitent and contrite children. As for the declaration of my faith it vvas abruptly in three howers donne by me, beſide none at Paris either helped me or ſaw it as yet, therefore it muſt needes be childiſhe. I pray you let it come to light both for the honor of the Church and my credit alſo, and for the diſcharging of my conſcience, beſides I made a ſolemne oth, that there is nothing but that it is true, euery good Chriſtian vvill thinke ſo, and I vvould you could learne his name that was in priſon neere me in the <hi>Gatehovvſe,</hi> &amp; aſke him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as for the reſolution of entring into religion, I haue choſen, meaning thereby to worke (by Gods grace) my ſaluation: I do it not for neede, for firſt I might &amp; may be (but I vvill not) a <hi>Carthuſian,</hi> although I neuer offred my ſelf. beſides going vvith a good Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Father to <hi>Says</hi> in Normandie, there in an Abbey of <hi>Sainct Martin,</hi> I vvas requeſted of moſt of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (as this Father can teſtifie) to enter into their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but I neither offred my ſelf there or to any other order but this: Nor minde to be of any but this of the Carmes, which I truſt I haue made choiſe of by Gods ſuggeſtion, not conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning any other order, al doubleſſe being of God, neither yet enter I into religion for neede or for deſperation, for I know that if the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of my ſinnes were more then the litle ſandes of the ſea, if I vnfainedly repent, by Contrition, Confeſſion, and Satisfaction as much as I can, that God will be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto me: to be ſhort, I vvill neither in any cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling diſpaire or preſume. for if in any thing, in this it is truely ſaid, <hi>In medio conſiſtit virtus.</hi> Briefly I will either attempt it vvith zeale, deuotion, and full deſire of working my ſaluation and the ſeruice of God, or els <hi>Manum de tabula,</hi> that is, I will leaue of betime, and not take the habit and afterwards, <hi>Valedicere habitui &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentui.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the reſt in your letter, if I ſtudy not to put
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5418:30"/>them in execution to th'vttermoſt of my power, ſurely my hart is more hardened then euer Pharoes hart was, ſeing that one not much inferiour to Moyſes, doth both by word of mouth and by writing ſpeake vnto me ſo louingly &amp; effectually. Thus leuing of to trouble you, I requeſt al your prayers for me, and as my bound dutye is, I will whiles I liue be your beades man. At <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your daily Oratour, Laurence Caddey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="confession">
            <pb facs="tcp:5418:31"/>
            <head>THE CONFESSION OF RICHARD BAINES PRIEST AND LATE STV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>of the Colledge of Rhemes, made after he vvas remoued out of the common gaile to his chamber.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S my miſerie &amp; vvickednes vvas greate which I vvill now ſet downe to the publiſhing of my ingratitude to God, the Church, and my ſuperiors, ſo vvas Gods iuſtice, mercy and prouidence meruelous towards me to ſaluation as I verely hope. Of al vvhich to the glory of Chriſt, and ſatisfaction of the holy Church and all her children whom I haue offended or ſcandalized, &amp; to mine owne vvorthy confuſion temporall, I intend to make this my publike confeſſion, that al that ſtand, may by my exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple beware of a fall, and ſuch as be fallen may thereby make haſt to aryſe againe.</p>
            <p>The very ground of my fall and of al the wickednes ether committed or inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, was my pride which droue me to a lothſomenes to liue in order and obedience, to conceipts of mine owne vvorthines and manifold diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentement of the ſchollarlike condition vvherein I liued, to an immoderat deſire of more eaſe, welth, and (which I ſpecially alſo reſpected) of more delicacie of diet and carnal delits then this place of baniſhment was like to yeld vnto me, though (vvo vnto me that could not ſee ſo fare before) the ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſtate in the Seminarie,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5418:31"/>vvhere I vvas in very honeſt compt and calling is in all points ſo good and happy, that moſt vviſe men wonder at Gods ſo mercifull and plentifull prouiſion for the competent maintenance of ſo many in ſuch a bleſſed trade of life and education.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, though I vvas not onely a ſtudent in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, but alſo a prieſt (though many vvaies I ſhewed and made my ſelf moſt vnworthie of that high degree) prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in dede in the ſight of my ſuperiors the ſtudy of holy ſcriptures as dewly required: yet in truth I moſt delited in prophane writers and the vvorſt ſort of them, ſuch as ether wrot againſt the truth or had leaſt taſt of religion, vvhereby the holy vvriters of my Chriſtian profeſſion &amp; prieſthood, began daily to waxe more and more tedious and lothſome vnto me, in ſo much that in the doing of ſuch publike exerciſes as by my courſe of ſtudy or my ſuperiors appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I often made, I had a delit rather to fil my mouth and the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors eares with daintie, delicat, nice and radiculous termes and phraſes, then vvith vvholſome ſound and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred doctrine.</p>
            <p>Whereby at leinght I had ſuch a liking of my ſelf, that through nouelties of wordes ioyned vvith pretty prouerbs, termes and mocking taunts, wherevnto by natural inclination and by my ſaid prophane vſage I vvas much giuen, I found meanes to inſinuat my ſelf to the familiaritie of ſome of the yonger ſort that me thought might eaſely be caried into diſcontentment &amp; to miſlike of rule and diſcipline and of ſubiection to their maiſters and gouernors: for vvhich purpoſe I vſed ordinarily ſome prety ſkoffes againſt euery of the elders of our howſe. Vndermining by art alſo, but in pretence of great playnnes and holy ſimplicitie certen very honeſt men, vvhom I thought knevv ſomewhat of my ſuperiors ſecrecie, the knowledge whereof (our lord God forgiue me) I purpoſed to abuſe as occaſion afterward ſhould be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the annoyance and great hurt as wel of the Catholike cauſe as of the Seminaries,
<pb facs="tcp:5418:32"/>our Preſident and other principal perſons, to whom by the lavv of God, nature, and by ſingular benefits donne to me I ovve all duety.</p>
            <p>With this I began by litle and litle to the ſcandal &amp; ruyne of diuers of the youth and other my fellovves, if God had not preſerued them by his ſinguler grace as vvel by my example of licentious life, as by vvicked words, to ſhew my miſlike of faſting and praying, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for fleſh pies or paſties in my chamber on fry daies at night, and omitting the diuine ſeruice preſcribed to men of my calling, often ieſting and ſkoffing thereat before ſome of my companions in vvhoſe ſecrecie &amp; loue toward me I had ſome affia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And then proceding farther and farther in vvickednes I began to mocke at the leſſer points of religion, vvhich is the high vvay to Hereſie, Infidelitie &amp; Athiſme. as to my great daunger I haue experience in myne owne caſe, ſo lamentable. deſiring al Chriſtian people to take head by my exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Proteſting to al the vvorld, that it is not reaſon, nor ſcriptures, nor the ſpirit of God, which are ſo much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by proteſtants, that leadeth any man to that dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſect, by vvhich one countrey is periſhed, but it is voluptuouſnes, ſenſualitie, pride, ambition ſingularitie delite and loue of mans ſelfe, that driueth downe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons laden vvith ſinne to this hereſie of the Proteſtants, and that the next dore, yea the next ſteape of this ſtaire is atheiſme and no beleefe at al. A fevv vvordes vvil ſerue a vviſe man.</p>
            <p>Wel when I had thus entangled my ſelf, &amp; for ſome daies proued that ſuch as I had vttered my euel heretical ſpeaches vnto kept al things cloſe, I bouldly adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tured vpon their familiaritie and ſecrecie to vtter diuers hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible blaſphemies in plaine termes againſt the principal points of religion, ſpecially to one perſon of myne owne calling vvho aftervvard (as I muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to the ſhame of th'ennemy) godly and trewly for both our good and ſaluations vttered the vvhole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto our ſuperior vvhich vvas Gods great mercy to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5418:32"/>me, for othervviſe I had doubtles periſhed for euer more.</p>
            <p>For a moneth ſpace or there abouts I delt vvith my ſaid fellovv bouldly not only by arguments and often communication to drawe him to hereſie, but alſo vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered to him my intention to goe into England, there to preach hereſie: and to annoye the common cauſe of Chriſts Church, and ſpecially this Seminary, the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ſuperiors thereof, as much as I could poſſibly: diſcourſing with him and declaring that there vvas no remedy, but the counſel muſt needes ſeeke the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Seminary, or els ſuſtaine their ſtate to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yned in time by it.</p>
            <p>Therevpon I vttered ſondry meanes vnto him, how firſt the preſident him ſelf might be made avvay, and if that miſſed, how the vvhole company might eaſely be poyſoned or othervviſe diſperſed further more offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my hand to gage, that the preſident ſhould not be a liue that daie tvvo yeres that I ſpake it, one of the yeres being now gone and yet he aliue: as I deſire God he may be many. This vvas often my deuiliſh communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and whether I ſhould not haue giuen this ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the counſel vvhen I came into England for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch of him and the ſaid Seminarie my dereſt nurce, my ſelf knovv not (to ſay he leſt) hovv farre the deuil vvould haue driuen me, vvho novv holy occupied my hart in hope of aduauncement in England by theſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes. For vvhich purpoſe I had alſo fraudulently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered certaine points of ſecrecie &amp; ſet them dovvne in vvriting with intent to giue the note of the ſame to the counſel, vvherein I rather detected my ovvne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice then any other thing, for the matters vvere of no importance in deede.</p>
            <p>In breefe this I muſt needes acknovvledge that I vvould haue done any of theſe impious iniuries rather then haue fallen from the preferment I hoped &amp; gaped after ſo inordinatly, our Lord of his infinite mercies for giue me that deteſtable treaſon againſt him and his
<pb facs="tcp:5418:33"/>Church: and the abhominable periurie diſſimulation &amp; fiction, vvhen for a vvhole moneths ſpace after I had diſcouered my minde to my fellovv, yet I ſaid Maſſe daily, ſought for leaue and viaticum of M. Preſident to goe home to encreaſe by preaching and al endeuours the Catholick cauſe, and toke an oth vpon the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts that I beleeued al points of the Catholick faith, and had no other purpoſe of going into England but for the aduancement of the ſame. And I deſire good M. Preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; the whole howſe euen for the bleſſed death and vvoundes of our Sauiour for vvhoſe ſake they ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine al this contradiction of me and other ſinners, to pardon and healp me by their praiers to true repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and remiſſion.</p>
            <p>And that good Prieſt my deare louing fellovv, whom I vvould haue had partaker of my vvicked and damnable reuoult I cry him mercy euen vpon my knees, and thanke him (though to the carnal vvordly man it might be compted an iniury that he diſcouered al my counſel vnto his ſuperiors and myne. for els I had been vvith out doute damned for euer more.</p>
            <p>But al this came of the ſweet mercies and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our Lord God and Sauiour vvho ouertooke and ouer raught me happely in the very courſe of my malice and damnable deſignements, and hath by his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable wiſedom, cauſed not onely my impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and other my bodely afflictions vvhich he procured for me at the very ſame time that I had thought to haue been in my ruffe and iolitie amongeſt his ennemies, but turned my very ſinnes and vvickednes to the good of his honor and my ſaluation: at the ſame time both deliuering his trevv and innocent ſeruaunts of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie and others vvhom my malice might haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyed, and me alſo, in moſt gracious &amp; miraculous ſort, his name be bleſſed therefore for euer more.</p>
            <p>And it is his goodnes that hath deliuered me from the accompliſhment of my vvicked deſires as powrably and miraculouſly al moſt as he did <hi>Saul</hi> perſecuting the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5418:33"/>Chriſtians, but vvith much more mercie then him, for that he found grace becauſe he did it of ignorance in incredulitie: vvhere I did al againſt my ovvne ſkill and conſcience: neuer doubting but the <hi>Catholick Romane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> vvas the onely <hi>true, Chriſtian, auncient and Apoſtolick faith,</hi> and vvorſhip of God: though I fained my ſelf for the atchiuing of my deteſtable deſigneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to doubt thereof and to haue ſome reaſonable motiues againſt the ſame, and ſought by al meanes poſſible to haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed my conſcience againſt that truth vvhich other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe I in hart beleeued.</p>
            <p>Novv therefore for the poore amends that lieth in me to make vnto Gods Church. I proteſt before the bleſſed Trinitie, and al the glorious company in heauen and by this publike vvriting vvhich I voluntarily make and ſubſcribe vvith mine ovvne hand: That I beleeue in al points the <hi>holy, Catholick, Apoſtolick</hi> &amp; <hi>Romane Church,</hi> ſubmitting my ſelf to her and the cheefe gouernor the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof our Lord and Maiſter <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>xiij.</hi> Chriſts ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Miniſter in earth: and do Deteſt, Accurſe, Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matize and Condemne from the botome of my hart, al <hi>Hereſies, Schiſmes</hi> and <hi>Sectes,</hi> and ſpecially the hereſies of <hi>Luther, Caluin,</hi> and al others vnto vvhich I might ſeeme by my outvvard wicked behauiour and diſſimulation to haue been enclined vnto: Deſiring God and our holy mother the Church, no othervviſe to haue mercie on me to ſaluation, then ſo long &amp; ſo farre as I keepe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and mantaine, to my povver the ſaid faith of our holy forefathers, taught &amp; ſet furth by the <hi>See Apoſtolick.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen in my chamber at Rhemes <date>the xiij. of May 1583.</date> in the preſence of <hi>M. Thomas Bailly</hi> Prieſt, <hi>M. Humphrey Ely</hi> Doctor of the Lavves. and <hi>M. Seth Foſter</hi> Prieſt.</dateline>
               <signed>I acknovvledge this to be mine owne act, <hi>Richard Baines Prieſt.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:5418:34"/>
            <head>THE SATISFACTION OF EDWARD OSBERNE PRIEST, TOVCHING <hi>his frailties, and fall from the Catholike Church, at his being in England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is almightie Gods great wiſedom &amp; mercy, that he hath beſides his other iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte iudgements either te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall or eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall vpon ſinners, ioyned alſo for moſt parte ſome great affliction and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of minde for a continuall inward checke and chaſticement of their offences euen in them ſelues, and in this life. which cauſed a great Clearke to ſaie, <hi>Thou haſte commaunded good Lord, and ſo it is, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnordinate appetite ſhould be a puniſhment to it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But no ſinne breadeth this internall vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much, as that which is committed againſt a mans owne ſkill and conſcience, ſpecially the voluntarie forſaking of that faith, truth, and religion vvhich God by his ſpirit in the <hi>Holy Church,</hi> and ſacred word, hath made him par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of. I ſpeake not of his caſe that impugneth of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice the knowne truth, as many arch-heretikes haue done, &amp; wickedly do, for that is a ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, &amp; ſuch often carieth about with them ſuch hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like torments of conſcience and deſperation, that they may be thought to beginne their da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation euen in this life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but I meane of others only, vvho by frailtie of the fleſh, feare of worldly diſtreſſes, doubte of temporall torments, and diſgraces, or ſomme other humane infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, be often driuen to yeld in ſomme points to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5418:34"/>threates, perſwations, or allurements, either of worldly freends, or goſtely enemies: euen theſe alſo, for that they haue denied Chriſt before men, preferred the body before the ſoule, hazarded heauen and their ſaluation, for the breefe, vncertaine, and miſerable ſtate of this tranſitorie vvorld, cary about with them in their breſt, farre vvorſe torments, then any are in the <hi>Tovvre,</hi> for the auoiding of vvhich, many times men make that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy choiſe, vvee ſee them doe.</p>
            <p>Of this miſerie (vvoe to me and my ſinnes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) I haue made to much experience: but I truſt to my euerlaſting ſaluation, as my mercifull Lord God hath now vſed the matter towards me. Who after I had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him, forſaken him, foreſworne him, wickedly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to certen blaſphemous articles, and made a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate abrenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciation of the pereles power and ſoueraine auctorite of Chriſts Lieutenant vpon earth, a flat denial of the Catholike faith, a plaine abiuration of my Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod, yea &amp; by the ſubtile crafte of the Churches deadly enemies, was induced, or rather driuen, to accuſe moſt traiterouſly and vniuſtly certen his holy, honorable, &amp; renoumed confeſſors, and to beare vnhappy vvitneſſe againſt them: after al this, yet loked vpon me from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vvith thoſe eyes of grace, by vvhich he conuerted <hi>Paule,</hi> reſtored <hi>Peter,</hi> pardoned <hi>Marie Magdalen,</hi> &amp; others not onely his fraile freends, but many his plaine perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, and by ſkourging my conſcience vvith contr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall remorſe, and dovvleful conſideration of my ſoule fall, and damnable condition, hath a leingth brought bitter teares out of my ſtonie hart, and called me againe out of that <hi>Sodom</hi> of our loſte countrey: and put me into the holy ſocietie, and communion of his body mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall, vvhich is his <hi>Church Catholike,</hi> th'only <hi>true mother</hi> of al the faithfull, the <hi>hovvſe of God,</hi> the <hi>pillar</hi> and <hi>eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of al truth.</hi> In vvhich only is al comfort, al grace, al benediction, and out of vvhich, as I novv knovv by mine owne experience, and by the certen vew of other mens caſes, with whom I haue of late in England con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſed,
<pb facs="tcp:5418:35"/>there is nothing but error, blindnes, doubte, or plaine deſperation.</p>
            <p>His name be bleſſed for euermore, that hath ſo povv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably and mercifully deliuered me his poore vnworthy ſeruant out of theſe and like miſeres, &amp; from the ſnares of ſuch, as doe nothing but ſeeke hovv by terror, or <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiuillian practiſe</hi> and pollicie, to driue men not to be of their religion (for ſuch as be the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon dealers in theſe caſes, God vvot haue none) but to ſeeme to be of that ſecte vvhich they would be counted of. Surely I can not for the honor of our countrie, and the dew reſpect I haue to office, and auctoritie (though to ſaie truth, they be not of any high function that vvorke vs theſe woes commonly) diſcouer their foule vncharitable, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian abuſe of my frailtie, in procuring my fall from God, and reuolt from the <hi>trevv Catholike Church.</hi> vvhich other vviſe to the ſhame of that irreligious he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, and mine owne confuſion in this vvorlde, that I might finde more mercie for the next, I vvould wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly lay open to the Chriſtian reader.</p>
            <p>This only which is the leaſt of thouſandes of their ſinfull, and craftie colluſions, I may not omit, to warne you, that they giue out, as often as any man of feare, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillanimitie, or any other worldly reſpect, yeldeth to their deſires, that it is Gods owne hande, &amp; miraculous vvorcke, proceding of the inuinceible force of their ſpirit, goſpel, and doctrine, againſt which, no learning, nor other obſtinacie of man may reſiſte. So ſurely they behaued them ſelues in my caſe, vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they knew it beſt them ſelues in their conſcience to be othervviſe, being the craftie procurers of my fall, and that they had not in my invvard opinion or iudgement (which vvas neuer I take God to vvitneſſe altered) though in outvvarde ſhevv ouerthrowen me.</p>
            <p>Novv my dearely beloued bretheren and vvho ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer els ſhall happe to reade this my pitiful complainte of my late diſtreſſes and tragicall actes, I doe proteſt vnto you before God, and al his ſainctes, and holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5418:35"/>that my yelding to their damnable deſires came not of any motion of the holy Ghoſt, by any probabilite of argument, or auctoritie ether of holy ſcripture, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, or any other reaſonable motiue, or for that I had any doubt vvhether the <hi>Catholike Romane religion</hi> vvere the trevv, and only ſauing faith and vvorſhip of God or no, for though I be neuer ſo ſimple, yet being in common ſence, and taking triall of both, in ſuch places, as I haue liued in, it is not poſſible that I, or any man ſhould in deede, and hart, preferre the proteſtants pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſed religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the <hi>Catholike faith,</hi> but to tell the plaine truth, and ſhame the Diuel, and my ſelf to, ſo farre as I follovved his peruerſe ſuggeſtions, al came of mine ovvne concupiſcence, euil deſire, and delicaces, which vvarred againſt me in my members, as th'Apoſtle ſaieth, and ſo did ouer rule in my ſpirit, captiuated, and cauſed me to yeld to fleſh and bloode, making me to feare to ſuffer any paines, or abandon my pleaſures for my Lord and maſters ſake, vvho had ſuffered ſo much, ſheade ſo many teares, ſo great abundance of innocent and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious blood for me.</p>
            <p>The aduerſaries threated me vvith <hi>Phalaris bull</hi> (ſo to call their torments) or as in truth, them ſelues termed it vnto me, <hi>Sir Ovven Hoptons ſchole,</hi> vvith dungeons and death alſo, except I vvould admit an vngodly oth, to anſwere truely to their captious and curſed interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, confeſſe ſuch things, as the feare and reuerence of God prohibited me, accuſe my ſelf, &amp; appeache the choſen ſeruants of God.</p>
            <p>Our Lord God gaue me many goodly motions at the very time of that combat, to reſiſte their terrors, and temptations, as he did alſo his manifold graces, &amp; good inſpiration, to contemne their ſwete promiſes of good benefices and other liuings, if I vvould conforme my ſelf vnto them: but (a laſſe) through my great ſinne &amp; frailtie, the aduerſaries for the time preuailed, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially my carnal freends, vvho, by I cannot tell vvhat ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſwete poyſon of fleſhly loue, and pretenſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb facs="tcp:5418:36"/>kindnes, do more deepely vvound and enchaunte their deareſt freends, then other men can doe their deadly enemies.</p>
            <p>Theſe lo are the arguments, and not any colour of ſcriptures, any learning of the heretikes, or any other probabilitie in the vvorld, that can moue any man to be of their religion: the ſame reaſons vvill as eaſely make one a Turke (I doe ſpeake it before God) as a proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For though thoſe, that be from their childehod brought vp in their Vniuerſites, or other their Scholes, and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: vvithout a ſpecial miraculous grace of God, can not lightly be of any other religion, becauſe they can not ordinarely beleeue excepte they heare, or reade ſome catholike trew teachers or vvriters, vvhoſe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings therefore the proteſtants hide from them with all diligence: yet none that euer hath ben a brode in the vvorld, and ſeene th'other, or that hath the good lucke to looke to the faith of our forefathers in our countrie, or any other Chriſtian countrie, can be in hart a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtante.</p>
            <p>And would God al the youthe of both vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, eſpecially my deare Brethren (whom God hath bleſſed vvith vvit, learning, and good nature) ſaw what loue, ſinceritie, ſweete and plaine dealing, is vſed in the Seminarie of Rhemes (vvhere I now by God his grace am) and how eaſely vpon a fevv daies conference and hearing, vvith out al Rackes, Feares, Forces, Tormentes, vvorldly allurementes, or preſermentes, by the only force of truth, and euidence of holy ſcriptures, and ſuch other plentiful proofes, as the Church of God, and al Catholike ſcholes haue, for al the articles in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, beſides the great difference betwixt the life, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and manners, ſeene here in Churches and ſcholes, and the wilde behauiour of our maiſters and Scholers in England. Or at leaſt, it vvere to be vviſſhed, that our fellow ſtudents in both the Seminaries, or other Catholikes, might haue the like fredo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come to thoſe vniuerſites, as theirs do hither, and there to trie, with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5418:36"/>out threates of impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; death, or terrifyinge, by calling men traitors, rebels, and I can not tell vvhat, to ſee then, vvhether their ſpirit or vvord (vvhereof they ſo childiſly vaunte them ſelues) could conuert any of this education in the holy Church, to their improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſecte.</p>
            <p>At the beginning I knovv, vvhen their vvares were freſh, and their nouelties ioyned to the promiſes and doctrine of luſte and licentiouſnes, they found ſome ſchollers, and may yet finde ſome, to follovv their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcences, but none trevvly (I thinke) either yong, or olde, that can be perſwaded by their arguments.</p>
            <p>They make much a doe, vvhen they gaine the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior aſſent of infirme perſons, vvhich in deede, are (thankes be to God) very fevve in compariſon of the great number of thoſe, that gloriouſly and conſtantly contemne their terrors &amp; perſwaſions, through whoſe forcible praiers, and merits, I verely thinke, God hath giuen me now at this time, and in manner al the reſt of their feeble brethren, grace &amp; mercy, that th'enemies there may haue confuſion by vs, where they looked for glorie, the vveake that fell, or vvere ſcandaliſed by vs, may riſe and repent vvith vs, and thoſe that ſtande may be vvarned by our frailtie, and by the admonition of the holy Apoſtle, to take head they fall not.</p>
            <p>For mine ovvne part (God knoweth) ſince I knevv vvhat religion ment, I vvas neuer (and leaſt of al, of late, vvhen they cauſed me to ſubſcribe to them) of their meaning. I ſubſcribed (our Lord God forgiue me) to that, which one <hi>Vvilliam Harte</hi> parler-preacher to my vncle <hi>Sir Robert Lane</hi> deuiſed, &amp; vvhich I neither knew of before, vvrote my ſelf, nor beleeued my ſelf.</p>
            <p>The very truth is, one <hi>Richard Levvis</hi> a miniſter, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Pariſh vvhere I vvas bred vp, &amp; where I then abode, a famous preacher in deede, but (as I am able to iuſtifie) a moſt infamous liuer, brought me to that vnlucky bargaine, as he vvas before the procurer of my firſt relenting, vvhich he may remember, by this token,
<pb facs="tcp:5418:37"/>that his <hi>energumicall</hi> ſpirit could not abide the ſigne of <hi>Chriſts Paſsion,</hi> portred in a glaſſe vvindow, in my Fathers Parler, vvhich vvas the Croſſe and vvoundes of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demer, vvith this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vvritten about the ſame, <hi>Pittey his paſsion, that cauſed our redemption,</hi> this goodly ſpeach he ſcraped out: &amp; let the reſt alone vvhich his diuiſiſhnes, no Chriſtian (I ſuppoſe) will allow, nor I, though fallen before, could like in him, but once fell into hote diſpute vvith him about the ſame, vvhoſe fooliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence (vvhich vvas, for that Chriſt is omnipotent, and a glorious God) I can not novv ſtande to reporte.</p>
            <p>Surely the very acquaintance with ſuch mens actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and vvordes vvhich they often lett fall in familiar com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, among ſuch as they deale vvith all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, would make a man abhorre them: one example may be of Fox, the auctor of the volume of Crackes &amp; many lies (I vvould ſaie, Actes &amp; monuments) to whom vvhen I had of late in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference, alleaged a place of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet. c.</hi> 1.11. for proofe that our good vvorkes vvere cauſe of our iuſtification, and ſaluation, the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv anſwered flatly: ſuch vvordes I doe not remember, but if <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſay, that wee are iuſtified or ſaued <hi>Per prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidia bonoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> operum</hi> (for ſo he is vvont to interlace his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh ſpeaches, with latten vvordes) I would ſay that he lied, becauſe Iame ſure that <hi>Paul</hi> hath the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby, and by diuers like thinges, I vvel perceue thoſe good fellovves meaſure all religo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their owne meere phanſie, caring in truth, nether for <hi>Peter,</hi> nor <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſt,</hi> further then their can vvrith they vvordes to their luſt. I am ſommething beholden to this man not vvithſtanding, for that, at our very firſt acquaintance of al, he made me partaker of a certen ſecrete, vvhich he ſaid he had not reueled to any man els, vz. <hi>That he vvas called by God him ſelf to make his nevv latten booke of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> Againe, at the ſame time very impertinently to our talke, he told me, that he had ſent an angell to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman <hi>Martin</hi> to change into ſingle penſe, for to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye them in almees: verely I laughed in my ſleue to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5418:37"/>heare this vaine hypocrite talke: thought I vvith my ſelf, <hi>Hypocrita cupit videri iuſtus.</hi> Theſe vvicked miniſters of Satan vvere they, that by their craft, pollices, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, procured my ſubuerſion, and ſubſcription of the ſaid articles, and other vniuſt actions.</p>
            <p>All vvhich articles, vvhich vvere ſeuen, I novv by this publike teſtimony doe reuoke, and recant of mine ovvne free wil, as before in hart, ſo novv openly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the vvorld, proteſting, that I vvill by the grace of God, liue, and die, in the communion, and felloſhip of the <hi>Catholike</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolike Church of Rome,</hi> and during life vvill obey in al ſpiritual cauſes, our holy Father <hi>Gregory the XIII.</hi> and his ſucceſſors in th'Apoſtolike ſeate Chriſts vicars in earth, the reuolte from vvhom, hath bene the cauſe of al theſe errors, ſectes, and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and that vvee can not liue in reſt and peace of conſcience in our vnhappy daies, and countrie, as our auncetors in times paſt did, but be thus ſpoyled, &amp; maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred, for no fellony, treſpas, or treaſon, but for hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that faith, which al our happy forefathers, and our ſelues vvere baptiſed in, and out of vvhich, I knovv there is no ſaluation in the next vvorld, nor grace in this. Beſeching Chriſt our merciful Sauiour, to pardon me that I denied him, and his truth, for feare of man and mortall paines.</p>
            <p>As I alſo humbly (for his ſake) deſire al Catholikes, vvhom I haue vniuſtly offended in this my fieblenes to forgiue, and pray for me, that I neuer fall to the like tentation againe: namely thoſe glorious confeſſors, vvhom I loue as mine ovvne ſoule, and honor as the choſen veſſels of God, vvho vvere iniured by my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew dealing. For I confeſſe, and acknowledge in my conſcience, that I ſhould haue ſuffered any torments in the vvorld, rather then haue vttered any their godly religious actes, to their dommage, vvhether it vvere trew, or falſe: and that I ſhould not, nor ought by Gods word, haue diſcloſed any ſuch thing, though I had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an oth to doe it, and to anſvvere to al interrogatories
<pb facs="tcp:5418:38"/>concerning the ſame: being aſſured that al ſuch othes, be vnlavvful, and ought not to be taken, nor be kept, if of frailtie they chaunce to be taken. Becauſe no man can binde him ſelf, neither by oth, vow, or any other obligation to God or man, to accuſe, or be wraye any innocent to the perſecutor: no ſuch othes (I ſay) binde, being one ſinne to take them, and an other, and that greater, to keepe them.</p>
            <p>But the thing a laſſe is novv paſt, and can not be amended in it ſelf, but only may be forgiuen, as I verely hope, it is both at God and mans hand, by this my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere confeſſing, humble crauing pardon, and poore pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike ſatisfaction, till the vvhich vvas done, I could neuer finde reſte in my vvounded conſcience, nor durſt approche to the holy Altar, to offer the deutiful giftes of my prieſthod: made much vnworthy of that high fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, through my ſaid greuous offence, and ſcandal. Which being now (as I hope) in our Lords mercy, and their great charitie, remitted, I ſhal daily vvith great comfort doe, during life, theſe ſoueraine duties of religion for them, as alſo (as I am moſt bound in deutie) for my deare Mother and al her Chriſtian offpringe, my dearely beloued Brethren and Siſters according to the fleſh, deſiring God, to reliue their zele vvith trew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, humbly beſeeching my louing Brother, &amp; Siſter, vvho bound them ſelues in a certen ſomme of mony for my good behauiour (ſo they cal the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie to their Engliſh procedings) not to impute my departure to any vnnaturall carleſneſſe of the loſſes, &amp; dangers that may fall vnto them by forfaiting their bande, by my retire ouer ſea: for God knovveth, it is the ſpeciall vvordly thing, that greueth me: but rather to accompte it a ſupplie of my patrimonie (vvhich vvould haue ſurmonted it much in valewe) &amp; a caſe of ſuch meere neceſſitie, both of my ſoule and body, as no intereſt of temporall goods vvhatſoeuer, may coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruaile it: and of their ſinguler brotherly and ſiſterly affection (if any extremitie ſhould be vſed towards
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5418:38"/>them in the matter) as I truſt verely their innocencie vvel knovven to the Counſel, &amp; their great earneſtnes, and diligence to gaine me to that religion (vvhich they of error and ill education thinke to be true) ſhal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them al courteſie, &amp; fauour therein, not to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pte the loſſe of monye, which one daye, either in this, or the next vvorld, may be redered by God, or man againe, for the health &amp; ſaluation of their owne fleſh &amp; blood: or at leaſt, if they thinke this not the waie to ſaluation, yet for quieting of his conſcience, againſt vvhich what ſoeuer a man doth, muſt needes be ſinne, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
            <p>Thus I ende deſiring them, and al Catholikes, my louing brethren in Chriſt, to pray and thanke God vvith me, for al his mercies, that he hath done to my ſoule, as it ſhal laude and bleſſe his holy name for euer more. Giuen at Rhemes this 19. of May, being the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Lord IESVS, to vvhom be al thankes and eternall glorie, for euer and euer. Amen. 1573.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By me a poore ſinner, your Brother in Chriſt, <hi>Edvvard Osberne Prieſt.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:5418:39"/>
            <head>THE SATISFACTION OF M. IAMES BOSGRAVE THE GODLY CONFESSOR <hi>of Chriſt, concerning his going to the Church of the Proteſtants at his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To al Chriſtians and al that profeſſe the Catholike faith, to al ſuch as are chained, Impriſoned, or othervviſe afflicted for the faith and religion of Ieſus Chriſt, peace and ſaluation.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed be the God and Father of our Lord IESVS CHRIST, the father of mercies and God of al comfort, vvho comforteth vs in al tribulation. I am merueilous heauy and ſorrow full at the hart, for that I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that there is a certen ſiniſter opinion ſprong &amp; ſpred abroade euery where of me, as though I had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that faith &amp; religion which had her beginning of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, vvas receiued of the Apoſtles, and Doctors, &amp; hath ben perfited &amp; ſealed, not onely with the blood and death of the vvorthy Martyrs, but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally with the blood and death of Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>Would to God that I had either neuer ben borne, or els that I had ben buried immediatly after my death. If I (borne of Catholike parents, nouriſhed &amp; brought vp vnder Catholike ſcholmaiſters, trained vp in learning in thoſe countries vvhere the Catholike religion dooth greatly proſper and floriſh) now at the length after my retorne into my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey to mine owne and my parents comfort: ſhould depart from that Church vvhich <hi>S. Paul</hi> calleth the piller &amp; ground of truth, ſhould deny Chriſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5418:39"/>our Lord, and breake my faith plight in baptiſme, and vvhereas al men did expect, that I ſhould haue borne grapes, to bring furth weedes.</p>
            <p>My deere and vvelbeloued brethren, to vvhom I write theſe fewe, vvhoſe glorie and ſaluation I ſeeke, and vvhom I beare in my bowels. I forſake my part of heauen, and vviſh neuer to ſee the good of God in the land of the liuing, and would that my name were blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the booke of life, if <hi>I</hi> euer either did or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, or as much as thought any ſuch thing, let me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be accurſed and a <hi>Maranatha,</hi> if I vvould either cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie Chriſt our Lord againe, or make void and fruſtrate the blood that the holy Apoſtles, and vvorthie martyrs haue ſhed: vvho al vvere ſlaine for that religion &amp; faith which Chriſt our Lord hath communicated &amp; reuealed vnto vs gratis: of the vvhich (religion and faith) I my ſelf am partaker and for the vvhich I am readie to ſuffer death.</p>
            <p>O wretch that I am, &amp; of al men the vnhapieſt, what hope of ſaluation could I haue, how durſt I lift vp mine eies to heauen, vvith vvhat face might I call Chriſt our Lord, Father, if I ſhould forſake his ſpouſe, the Church our Mother? I knovv (moſt louing brethren) that there is no more ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be looked for out of the Church, in the which I beleeue my ſelf to be vvith you: then there was out of the <hi>Arch of Noë,</hi> which bare the type &amp; figure of the <hi>Catholike</hi> &amp; <hi>Apoſtolike Church.</hi> Do not yee therefore giue ouer light credit to euery flying tale, for I know that the ende ſhall proue al theſe rumors that haue ben ſpred of me, to be falſe and fayned.</p>
            <p>For I hope brethren (and this is my deſire) that I ſhalbe bound vvith the ſame chaine, and for the ſame faith, that you are, &amp; I truſt to be partaker both of your tribulations &amp; your rewards. God forbid that I ſhould glorie (to vſe the ſpeach of the veſſel of election, and of the Doctor of the Gentils, vvith out al arrogancie and pride) ſauing in the Croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. I beſeech you therefore (as yet not being bound, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure
<pb facs="tcp:5418:40"/>to be bound in our Lord) that you remaine, and walke vvorthily in the vocation religion and faith to vvhich you are called: and that you be ready to ſhed your blood for the ſame.</p>
            <p>You haue heard, that I vvas become a Proteſtant, I call God and his Angels to vvitnes (brethren) that this hath ben mine election and that full often (if I ly, then I praie God, I neuer ſpeake more) that I had rather be a Turke or a Ievv, then a Proteſtant, that is, to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouled among thoſe that haue renied the faith of Chriſt. There be many I knovv vvhich haue heard me (albeit vvith murmuring and indignation) vtter theſe vvords. For it were better for me in deede, neuer to haue knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vvay of truth, then after the knowledge thereof to ſtart back from it. If therefore (my freends) the fame of my retorne into my countrey be come vnto your eares, if peraduenture theſe naughtie reports of me be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly talked of amongſt you: if you do ouer expect any thing of me that perteineth to the duty of a brother, freend or kinſman of yours, &amp; that vvhich the name of a Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dooth require, vvhich is borne, brought vp, and by the ſpace of many yeres as it vvere confirmed in the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> and <hi>faith,</hi> perſwade your ſelues for certain, that I will (by Gods aſſiſtance) ſatisfie your expectation.</p>
            <p>You haue heard peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture, that I vvould go to the Church. God almightie (in vvhoſe ſight I am, &amp; ſpeake, and vvho is the ſearcher of the hart and reines of men) dooth know, that I neuer went to the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts church vvith the mind to pray, or to allow and profeſſe their ſect, neither by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraint or free accord, to ſeeme by any meanes to approue by conſent and liking this religion, which they terme, reformed: but I vvent ſometimes &amp; that but ſeldoome, vvhen I thought it good, only for to ſee their rites, and then manner of preaching and doing, and to make mine Engliſh tong more prompt &amp; ready. Nor do you not thinke, that, that vvhich is lavvfull to ſome one for certen cauſes, is conuenient to al men,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5418:40"/>for I vvould not counſel other men to go to the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants church, yea I haue diſwaded men from it aboue a thouſand times: and haue ſhewed them, that it was in no caſe lawful: becauſe, that he that loueth danger, ſhall fall into it: neither vvould I haue gone to their conue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles for any thing, if I had know that I ſhould haue giuen occaſion of ſcandall.</p>
            <p>You haue heard (and do maruel at it) that I am at liberty, and therefore you ſuſpect that I am retorned to my vomit. Deerely beloued, I am of al lyers the va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, if I do not enuie you your chaines, your priſon, your baniſhment, your gard, your loſſe of goods, your tribulation for Chriſt: and perſwade not your ſelues I praie you, that I do reioyce in this my fortune and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, but rather that it is ſorrovvful &amp; loth ſome vnto me, that I am not vvorthy to ſuffer contumely for the name of Ieſus. Therefore I attribut my liberty to the clemency of God almightie, to the courtoſie of the Q. Maieſties honorable and vviſe Counſellers, I impute it to mine owne miſhap, &amp; to my great ſinnes: but that which is differred is not altogether taken avvaie. If I vſed doutfull words before the Q. Maieſties counſel, for the vvhich they ſet me at liberty, I haue interpreted them more plainely by my letters, which I haue novv ſent to the Q. moſt honorable &amp; ſage Counſellers. But put the caſe I yelded vnto them: vvhy brethren, ought I to attribute more to my ſelf, then to moſt bleſſed <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> moſt holy <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> moſt ſtout <hi>Thomas of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> of the vvhich, the two former were Popes, and al after the denial of Chriſt, obteined pardon, and ſhed their blood for the <hi>Catholike faith.</hi> Be you not therefore ſeduced, vvith the vvicked example of one man, but ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtoutly &amp; dwell in this church, in which wee haue ben borne and bred: the vvhich Chriſt our Lord hath built and brought forth vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors: vvhoſe ruines do begin now after a ſort to be repaired and reſtored.</p>
            <p>But to draw to an ende, I beſeech you brethren by
<pb facs="tcp:5418:41"/>by the bowels of the mercie of Ieſus Chriſt, by that charitie vvherewith he ſo loued vs that he vouchſaued to be hanged on a tree for vs, by his croſſe, his wounds, by the nailes and ſpeare (vvhich are the badges of our Sauiour) that you, be not frighted nor moued vvith falſe reportes, th'end wil proue al: and perſwade your ſelues, that as I am partaker of one countrey with you, ſo am I partaker of one Church, one faith, one religion, one doctrine, vvith you. I thought good to write this letter, to witnes thereby vnto you, that I am of the ſame religion, in vvhich I vvas borne againe by baptiſme and for the vvhich I am moſt ready to dye vvith you. I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re you alſo to pray vnto Chriſt Ieſus crucified for me, to giue me grace to direct al my thoughts, vvords and works, to the glory of his moſt holy name, to mine ovvne ſaluation and to the profite and commoditie of my countrey. Let vs alſo pray continually and vvith a common accord, that Chriſt our Lord would preſerue the Queenes Maieſtie, and her ſage Counſellers, and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate them vvith al truth, that al their beginnings &amp; proceedings te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to the glory of almighty God. Chriſt Ieſus embrace vs al in the bowels of his mercies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme vs and make vs al in one agreement in the Church which he hath founded vvith his moſt precious death.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare yee vvell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5418:41"/>
            <head>AN ADMONITION TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are no more of regard, as farre as vve yet heare, that haue relented al this long &amp; perilous time of practize and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſauing <hi>M. Aufild,</hi> and <hi>M. Govwe,</hi> the former in <hi>England,</hi> through extreeme feare of torments yelding onely to goe to their church once, and that vvith many qualifications: the other in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> vpon other frailtie, ſpecially for deſire to retorne home and enioye the commodities temporal that God had giuen him in his countrey: vvho both ſtreight vpon their fall (being in regard of humane frailtie not great) vvept bitterly, haue done penaunce accordingly, vvritten their letter to
<pb facs="tcp:5418:42"/>our Preſidet in <hi>Rhemes</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> readines to doe any ſatisfaction for the ſcandal and offence committed, and ſo be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to Gods Church againe, and haue done ſince that, and doe, al they can poſsibly for th'aduauncement of the Catholike faith. Vvhoſe like pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike acknovvledge of their offence ſhould here haue been ſet furth, but that the ſame could not be ſo ſpeedely ſent hither as the diſpatch of theſe other vvas compted neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Onely in al this (gentil reader) I deſire the to marke for thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the mercies of God: hovv in this lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g combat vvith ſo forcible and povvra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ennemies according to the fleſh, vvho vva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t no meanes vvorldly, either to force by feare of death &amp; torments, or to tempt by pleaſure proffit &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, or to entangle by art and pollicie, he hath giuen vs his poore
<pb facs="tcp:5418:42"/>ſeruaunts and ſouldiars, not onely to fight, ſtand, hold out, &amp; haue aſſured hope of victory ouer the aduerſaries, but to haue it vvith ſo ſmall a loſſe, by the death of ſo fevv, vvith the fall or vvounding of ſo fevv, ſo eaſely reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered againe to farre more aduantage of the cauſe, as our Lord hath of his grace vſed the matter, then if they had neuer had experience of their ovvne infirmitie, and of the neceſsitie of his holy ayde, by vvhom onely vve are vpholden in this ſpiritual fight for our faith, and defence of his deare Spouſe our Mother the Church, vvhich by no povver of man or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel can be ouerthrovvne.</p>
            <p>Fare vvel gentil reader, and make thy profit to ſaluation, of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of our frailtie, vvhereby thou ſeeſt Gods ſtreinght to be perfited in our infirmitie, and our vveakenes to
<pb facs="tcp:5418:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>be ſuſtained by the force <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his grace, to him be al honor and glorie. Amen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The firſt of Iune 1583.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5418:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
